<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Considerations touching the dissolving or taking away the court of chancery and the courts of iustice depending upon it with a vindication or defence of the law from what is unjustly charged upon it, and an answer to certain proposals made for the taking away, or alteration, of it.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5918</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12396355</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12396355</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61188</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61188)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 935:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Considerations touching the dissolving or taking away the court of chancery and the courts of iustice depending upon it with a vindication or defence of the law from what is unjustly charged upon it, and an answer to certain proposals made for the taking away, or alteration, of it.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 75, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by F.L. for Thomas Heath, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Courts --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61188:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CONSIDERATIONS Touching the DISSOLVING OR TAKING AWAY The COURT of CHANCERY, AND The Courts of Iuſtice depending upon it, VVITH A Vindication or Defence of the Law from what is unjuſtly charged upon it, AND An Anſwer to certain propoſals made for the taking away, or alteration, of it.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Cicero pro Cluentio.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Civitas ſine Lege, ut corpus ſine mente.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Leo Imp. in proaem. Conſtit. Novellarum.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunt Leges tanquam Cuſtodes vitae noſtrae.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed by <hi>F. L.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Heath,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:61188:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61188:2"/>
            <list>
               <head>The Contents.</head>
               <item>OF the Court of Chancery, <hi>Chap. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The great inconveniences which will happen by the diſſolving of it to the whole frame and body of the Laws and Iuſtice of this nation, <hi>ch. 2.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Beſides other ſad effects and conſequences will be brought upon the people by it, <hi>ch. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the Laws are not in themſelves evil, but are only abuſed by the people, <hi>ch. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That to put down or overturn the Chancery, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Courts of Iuſtice which depend upon it, will be ſo much againſt the former cuſtomes and reaſons of this or any other nation, as it is not to be preſidented, <hi>ch. 5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the very being of Parliaments is preſerved by the Laws, and that ſo great a diſtemper and diſturbance as will come by the taking away of the Laws, will by a neceſsity of Iuſtice, and better ordering of affairs, bring them, by a revolution of time, back again into their old channel, <hi>ch. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:61188:3"/>
               <item>That the erecting of ſo many new Courts as are propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or cutting and tranſlating the great Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> into ſo many little Courts and Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, will, beſides the before-mentioned inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, not only be very prejudicial to the State, but to the people, <hi>ch. 7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And not only raiſe up again thoſe old grievances which were formerly the cauſe of diſuſing, or reſtrayning, the Sheriffs Turnes, County Courts, Court Barons, and Hundred Courts, and ſuch-like petty Iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but far exceed them, <hi>ch. 8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the annexing of a Iuriſdiction or power of equity to every or many of ſuch new Courts, will much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the peoples grievances, and turn that little Law which ſhall be left, into a courſe of arbitrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>ch. 9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That in the right adminiſtration of Iuſtice, there is a neceſsity of Lawyers, and men of skill and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>ch. 10.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:61188:3"/>
            <head>CONSIDERATIONS Touching The Diſſolving, OR Taking away, the <hi>COURT</hi> of <hi>CHANCERY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Parliament</hi> that intends to bleſs and make the <hi>Nation</hi> happy, are to conſider what may beſt advance it.</p>
            <p>In order to which, as they may claim the Prayers and <hi>obedience</hi> of thoſe they repreſent; So on the other ſide, the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples great concernment, in what ſhall be acted or ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them, is entitled to a modeſt and well-ordered <hi>liberty</hi> of addreſs, and advices, not only in the general, but in particular alſo, to the end that every part, how little ſoever, of the Body Politique, may be either heard, or rightly underſtood, before any alteration or Sentence ſhall goe out againſt it; Eſpecially when their Liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
<pb facs="tcp:61188:4"/> Freehold, and Poſterities, are to be the preſent and immediate Sufferers in it.</p>
            <p>For it could never be intended by the <hi>Lawes,</hi> or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of this <hi>Nation,</hi> or is indeed imaginable, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> can (like a <hi>Deity</hi>) ſee thorow, and know all things at once, or before-hand, or <hi>judge</hi> of what can be objected or ſaid in any particular caſe or concernment, without hearing parties or defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>The Juſtice and reaſon whereof may be <hi>exemplified</hi> from <hi>God</hi> himſelf, who being not only <hi>Omniſcient,</hi> but <hi>Omnipotent,</hi> would not think it fit to condemn <hi>Adam,</hi> untill he had heard what he could ſay for himſelf.</p>
            <p>Whence the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi> the <hi>Civil, Canon,</hi> and <hi>Common Lawes,</hi> and all the <hi>Parliaments</hi> of this <hi>People</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> have not only made it their Rule, but their Practice, to hear both parties, without which no Sentence or Judgement can be ſaid to be juſt or valid, (though the parties that did it ſhould intend it well, and give as juſt a Sentence as poſſibly they could) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that generally received <hi>Maxim</hi> amongſt all <hi>Nations, Qui judicaverit altera parte inaudita, aequum licet, ſtatuerit, injuſtus eſt.</hi> Upon which conſideration of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and that moſt antient and uninterrupted <hi>cuſtome</hi> of it, and the reaſon of all <hi>Nations</hi> and Men of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</p>
            <p>It is hoped, that the now <hi>Parliament</hi> (according to the antient courſes of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and thoſe ſage and ſucceſsfull Cuſtomes of thoſe Sonnes of <hi>Liberty</hi> the <hi>Romans;</hi> who, in the <hi>Rogation</hi> and promulgation of their Laws, did not only hear, but demand what the People, and thoſe that were to experiment the ſweet or ſowr of it, had to ſay againſt it) will give leave to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61188:4"/> thoſe that have been bred up, laid out their Fortunes, and ſpent a great part of their lives in Chancery, and well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, to be heard, concerning the preſervation of what ſhall be good, or the taking away of any thing that ſhall appear to be evil in it, before they ſhall proceed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe <hi>Propoſals,</hi> which have been made unto them for the diſſolving of that <hi>Court;</hi> And for the better ſanisfaction of that ſmall part of the People, which tire the <hi>Supreme Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> 
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">1</note> with their <hi>wild</hi> Propoſals, to repreſent unto them what that Court is, which that kind of People would have the Parliament to put down.</p>
            <p>The great <hi>inconveniences</hi> which will happen by it, to the <note place="margin" type="runSum">2</note> whole frame and body of the Laws, &amp; <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of the Nation.</p>
            <p>Beſides other ſad effects and Conſequences will be <note place="margin" type="runSum">3</note> brought upon the People by it.</p>
            <p>That the Laws are not in themſelves evil, but are only <note place="margin" type="runSum">4</note> abuſed by the People.</p>
            <p>That to put down, or overturn the <hi>Chancery,</hi> and ſo <note place="margin" type="runSum">5</note> many Courts of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> which depend upon it, will be ſo much againſt the former Cuſtoms and reaſons of this, or any other <hi>Nation,</hi> as it is not to be <hi>preſidented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the very Being of <hi>Parlements</hi> is preſerved by the <note place="margin" type="runSum">6</note> Laws; And that ſo great a diſtemper and diſturbance, as will come by the <hi>taking</hi> away of the Laws, will by a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Juſtice, and better ordering of affairs, bring them by a revolution of Time, back again into their old Chanel.</p>
            <p>That the erecting of ſo many new Courts as are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, <note place="margin" type="runSum">7</note> or cutting the great Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> into ſo many little Courts and <hi>Iurisdictions,</hi> will, beſides the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned inconveniences, not only be very <hi>prejudicial</hi> to the <hi>State,</hi> but to the people.</p>
            <p>And not only raiſe up again thoſe old grievances, which <note place="margin" type="runSum">8</note> were formerly the cauſe of diſuſing or reſtraining the <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs</hi>-Turns, <hi>County</hi>-Courts, Court-<hi>Barons</hi> and Hundred-Courts,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61188:5"/> &amp; ſuch like petty Iurisdictions, but far exceed them.</p>
            <p>That the annexing of a jurisdiction or power of equity <note place="margin" type="runSum">9</note> to every or many of ſuch new Courts will much increaſe the Peoples grievances, and turn that little Law, which ſhall be left, into a courſe of arbitrarineſſe.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> What that Court is, which they would have taken away.</head>
               <p>THe Court of Chancery (not to trouble the Reader with what is more largely declared by <hi>Crompton</hi> in his Iurisdictions of Courts, Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> in his Gloſſary, and Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> in the fourth part of his <hi>Inſtitutes,</hi> and the known benefits, which redound and come unto very many of the People by it (for thoſe that are reſtrained by it from their oppreſſions are not always well-pleaſed with it) is the <hi>conſcience</hi> of the <hi>Supreme Authority,</hi> to qualifie the ſeveritie of the Laws, when they happen to be ſo in ſome particular caſes, without taking away thoſe Laws, or break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, or opening a gap to Ten Thouſand mens incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, to give relief to ſome one particular man, which without thoſe general remedies and applications of <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> could not otherwiſe be avoided; And as to the <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Latine</hi> part of it, and granting out of Writes <hi>Remedial,</hi> will appear to be a <hi>Court</hi> as antient as the Reaſon or Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the <hi>Nation;</hi> from which all the other Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall, County-Courts, Sheriffs-Turns, Court-Leets,</hi> and <hi>Baron,</hi> and all other <hi>Courts</hi> inferiour, may truly be ſaid to have their beginning; the <hi>Matrix,</hi> or Womb of all our <hi>Fundamental</hi> Laws, either before or ſince <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which had its birth and being from it; A Court, where the <hi>Genius loci,</hi> and <hi>Salus populi,</hi> like Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the Womb of the <hi>Creation,</hi> reſides, to give out its ordinary adminiſtrations of Juſtice for the good of the people, and is for that purpoſe as the <hi>Soul</hi> to the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61188:5"/> in the direction and ſubſiſtence of it; And the <hi>head,</hi> to which all the <hi>Nerves</hi> and Sinews of it are joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; The <hi>repoſitory</hi> (in the abſence of <hi>Parliaments</hi>) of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> in all caſes where the helps of <hi>Parliaments</hi> were not neceſſary; The <note n="a" place="margin">St. German de funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Leg. Angliae, cap. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Custom</hi> of the Nation; The <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cina Juſtitiae,</hi> the place or work-houſe of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> The original and Authority of all mens Aſſurances and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyances by <hi>Fines</hi> and <hi>Recoveries;</hi> The Preſerver of their Rights and Eſtates in them; The <hi>primum mobile</hi> of all or moſt of our proceedings at Law; The principal Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary, <hi>Amanuenſis,</hi> or <hi>Regiſter</hi> of the <hi>Supreme Authority,</hi> and which bears <hi>Record</hi> unto it; The place, whither the Petitions in Parliament, that could not be diſpatched, were uſually referred; The <hi>Fountain</hi> and <hi>Chanel,</hi> by which Juſtice, Reaſon, and Equity, was upon any of the peoples neceſſities or complaints conveyed unto them, and the <hi>Magazine,</hi> ſtore-houſe, and <hi>diſpenſatory</hi> of all Writts remedial, and in which all the peoples rights, liberties, and properties are ſo <hi>concentred,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate, as they muſt either <hi>die</hi> or <hi>live</hi> with it, and is, as ſaith the laſt <hi>Parliament,</hi> no longer ago than in <hi>April,</hi> 1641. by a long uſage and preſcription grown to be, as it were, <hi>Lex Terrae,</hi> 
                  <note n="b" place="margin">M. <hi>Hides</hi> Argument before the Lords in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by Order of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</note> the diſſolution wherof, muſt of neceſſity produce very many miſchiefs and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The miſchiefs and inconveniencies which will happen to the whole Frame and Body of the <hi>Laws,</hi> and Iuſtice of the Nation, by the diſſolution of it.</head>
               <p>FOr it will not only take away the equitable and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> part of it, conſiſting of Bils, Anſwers, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees (being a latter part of the buſineſs of it) to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61188:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Frauds,</hi> Combinations, <hi>Truſts,</hi> Secret uſes, and the like, and moderate, or take away the rigor of <hi>Laws,</hi> and reſcue men out of the hands of ſuch as would op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them, by putting <hi>extremities</hi> upon them; but the old and moſt antient part of it, conſiſting of writs of <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> which no other Court can grant in a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; For that the <hi>Chancery</hi> was always to be open, to give remedies where it can to the people; The Sealing and Inrolling of <hi>Letters Patents</hi> and <hi>Pardons;</hi> Inrolling of <hi>Treaties</hi> and Leagues with Forein <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States;</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king or granting out Writs or <hi>Summons</hi> of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Edicts,</hi> Proclamations, <hi>Charters,</hi> Protections, ſafe Conducts, or for Elections of <hi>Knights</hi> of the Shire, <hi>Burgeſſes, Parliament</hi> men, and Coroners; Writs of <hi>moderata miſericordia</hi> where any were too much amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and of a reaſonable part of goods for Widdows and Orphans; Patents for <hi>Sheriffs; Cercioraries</hi> to remove <hi>Records</hi> and falſe Judgements in inferior Courts; Writs of <hi>Audita querela</hi> and <hi>Scire Facias;</hi> Inrollments of Deeds betwixt partie and partie concerning their lands, eſtates or purchaſes; Taking <hi>recogniſances,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out of extents upon Statutes and recogniſances for payment of moneys, or ſecuring of Contracts; Writs remedial or magiſterial, Commiſſions of appeal, <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> for the <hi>Peace,</hi> and many other things not here enumerated, tending either to the well-being or conſervation of Juſtice; And in a word almoſt all the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the Nation (<hi>Parliaments</hi> being proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>pro arduis,</hi> and <hi>eminent</hi> occaſions, not determinable by any other Court.)</p>
               <p>Make all the Decrees of <hi>Chancery</hi> and <hi>Injunctions</hi> gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt unconſcionable acts or proceedings at Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Law,</hi> when the ſaid Court ſhall not have any being
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61188:6"/> to protect or maintain them, to be contemned; and the parties put again to new vexations and troubles; increaſe and encourage deſperate ſwearings and perjuries, in the Intervals, betwixt the putting-down of the old Court and erecting of a new.</p>
               <p>Enervate, and put into a ſuſpition, all thoſe very many judgements and decrees, which have been founded upon the proceedings of it; as is demonſtrable enough in the Acts of the Courts of <hi>Star</hi>-Chamber, <hi>Requeſts,</hi> and High <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> Courts of <hi>Honour,</hi> and <hi>Marches</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> and the <hi>North,</hi> upon their diſſolution.</p>
               <p>Take away the <hi>preſcription</hi> and <hi>birth</hi>-right of all the free-born people of <hi>England</hi> to their <hi>Laws</hi> and cuſtoms; And by diſſolving the <hi>Chancery,</hi> and ſo many Courts of Law and reaſonable Cuſtoms as depend upon it, Leaves them only ſome Statute and penal Laws to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their Proprieties: For, as many of them as they can get again, muſt be by a new grant, which thoſe that have had right of <hi>Common</hi> or <hi>Copy-hold</hi> (being of a far leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment,) and loſt it, by pulling down an old <hi>Tenement</hi> and building up a new, or taking a Leaſe of their <hi>Copy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> eſtate, may gueſs how prejudicial it may be in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matters.</p>
               <p>Obſtruct, and put to a ſtand all aſſurances, contracts and bargains, which are every <hi>minute</hi> going and paſſing amongſt the people.</p>
               <p>May diſturb, and prejudice many men in their eſtates and properties, as well as <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in their power and authority over them; And put them on to jeaiouſies, <hi>Scruples,</hi> and queſtionings of the preſent authority, when they ſhall have none, of the Cuſtoms, of the old, which they took to be reaſonable, left to goe along with them, or perſwade to an obedience to it; And may be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61188:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> but as the throwing down at once of an old Park pale, upon hopes that the Deer will be perſwaded to tarry in, upon an expectation of a new.</p>
               <p>All the writs and Commiſſions made out and retorna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in Chancery will be to ſeek for a validity, as to their execution or retorn.</p>
               <p>All the cauſes now depending, enough to take up (if they ſhould lay aſide the work of beginning and emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencie of new cauſes) the unwearied skill, endeavours, and time of the preſent <hi>Lords Commiſsioners</hi> and Mr. of the <hi>Rolls,</hi> for ſeven years (who by former motions and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings are well acquainted with the nature of many of them, and by that means may be more skilfull in the way of determining of them, than any Committee, which can be choſen) will then be put to the deciſion of Strangers, or ſuch as may be as long again in finiſhing of them.</p>
               <p>And if the heap of new cauſes ſhould be undertaken by the ſame men at the ſame time, may make ſuch a ſtop, as may ſwell up the <hi>diſcontents</hi> of the people, to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, or breaking down the banks of any new erected Courts or <hi>Committees</hi> for it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Common</hi>-pleas betwixt partie and partie, which hath its <hi>originals</hi> and Commiſſions from it, will expire, for it cannot hold plea without it.</p>
               <p>All that our former Laws, appointed to be done in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain preſcript ways and times, as the bringing of <hi>Forme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons</hi> in diſcender or remainder; and all thoſe ſeveral ſorts of remedial writs, in the <hi>Natura Brevium,</hi> and <hi>regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> (being like ſo many ſeveral ſorts of approved and experimented phyſicks, and remedies prepared, boxed, and laid-up by a long obſervation and experience for the future, for the ſeveral diſeaſes of mens eſtates, rights or liberties) will become uſeleſſe.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:61188:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>All the many neceſſary and wholſome powers, and buſineſſe, which former <hi>Parliaments</hi> have by their many Acts and Laws intruſted to the <hi>Chancery,</hi> will be laid aſide; and the people ſent to look out new ways, or remedies, where they can find them, and take-up that which their <hi>forefathers</hi> refuſed as inconvenient, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of that they formerly received ſo much benefit by.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Magna Charia,</hi> and its 30 times confirmation, which <note place="margin">17 E. 1, ca. 7. 25 E. 1. Ca. 1, 2, 3, &amp; 4.</note> was delivered with Curſes and <hi>Anathemas</hi> to the Infrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and commanded to be read once a year in <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> againſt which no law was to be made, upon the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of being void, was got, and continued, with ſo much blood of our Anceſtors, and forbids the denial of juſtice to any ſhould ask for it, gave the Tryals <hi>per Pares,</hi> and that none ſhould be impriſoned or <hi>diſſeiſed,</hi> but by original writs (then and ever ſince iſſuing out of <hi>Chancery</hi>) and due proceſſe of Law; And the care ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken formerly that <hi>Nullus recedat a Cancellaria ſine remedio,</hi> will be to no purpoſe when the <hi>Court</hi> is put down that ſhould grant it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Wolf</hi> may eat the <hi>Lamb,</hi> when there ſhall be none to ſtretch out their hand to deliver the oppreſſed. All that was good in that Court, and beneficial for the people, (for certainly it being ſo antient, and of ſo long a continuance, could not be ſo unhappy, as to have no good thing, nor proceeding in it) will be put under the ſame <hi>fate,</hi> as the bad, wherein it will be loſt; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by a new conſtitution, or a particular enumeration of them in a new eſtabliſhment, (which will find ſtore of difficulties) it ſhall happen to be revived, there being a great difference betwixt what a <hi>Court</hi> hath incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in it by a cuſtome, and what it muſt get and have by a new authority for, and may tend to the greateſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61188:8"/> alteration in the adminiſtration of Juſtice that ever hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to a Nation, and produce many other ſad effects and conſequences will follow upon it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Other ſad effects and conſequences will follow upon it.</head>
               <p>FOr above 2000 Families, whoſe livelihoods, labours, and fortunes, have been laid out in the labour, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance of this ſo high and neceſſary a Court, will, without ſome recompence or ſubſiſtance made or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for them, be utterly undone, and expoſed to Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery; the <hi>rather,</hi> for that they are not like Husbandmen, or day-<hi>Labourers,</hi> that can fit themſelves for common and ſervile labours. Above 20000 Families of Townſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Citizens, in or neer <hi>London,</hi> (whoſe induſtry and maintenance depended much upon the reſidence, and ſtudy of the Laws at <hi>London,</hi> (beſides the Profeſſors of the Law, and thoſe many families are maintained by it) will be either totally undone, or much impaired in their eſtates, and livelihood; Many Thouſands of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termen, the ſtrength and ſubſiſtence of our Sea-affairs, and Thouſands of Artificers, and other people who live by Trading and travelling to <hi>London,</hi> will be ruined; and that <hi>City,</hi> which by its Situation and Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to the Sea, the riches, skill, and correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of her Merchants, and a long fixed Trade and cuſtom, is the fitteſt of all this body Politique, to make a heart of; And was wont to be the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Laws, and Courts of Juſtice, whither all the people flocked for Commerce, as well as Juſtice, will by the deprivation of them, be little better than as a <hi>City</hi> two parts in three deſtroyed; or burnt: And be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61188:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſo put into a continual leſſening or decay, as the rents and profits of at leaſt a doſen neighbouring <hi>Counties,</hi> whoſe proviſions and commodities did, by their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood and trading thither, bear a higher price than in other remote places, will be diminiſhed, as much as a half, or one part in three, in their Eſtates and manner of living, and diſabled to pay, as they have done, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Taxes or Aſſeſſments, when they ſhall be called for: And not only thoſe, but all the other Counties and Cities of <hi>England,</hi> as they ſhall neerer relate or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to thoſe Counties, be made the worſe for it; But the ſmalleſt Towns or Villages, or moſt remote parts of the Land, will quickly come to be wofully ſenſible of the diſtemper or decay of ſuch a principal and vital part of the Nation; The ruine, or but diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring whereof, by the putting down of the Law and Courts thereof, may prove to be a cauſe of many more, and greater inconveniences, than if that great and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Manufacture or Trade of <hi>Clothing</hi> ſhould be prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; then the altering or turning the courſe of all the <hi>Rivers,</hi> or known chanels, or currents of waters, or the ſtopping or taking away the Highwayes, and known <hi>roads</hi> of the Nation, could bring upon the People.</p>
               <p>Whilſt they that thus beſpeak their own <hi>ruine,</hi> do not yet, perhaps, ſo fully take into their conſideration, as they may hereafter, when it ſhall be too late, that the <hi>Chancery,</hi> and the Courts of <hi>Juſtice</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> are as the <hi>Aſylum's</hi> or ſanctuaries of all that are oppreſſed; the <hi>Protection</hi> of the people, and (next under God, and the Supreme Authority) the moſt certain rules of their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and properties. And that the liberties of the People do reſide, and have their Being in the Laws and Courts of Juſtice, as the <hi>vital</hi> and animal ſpirits doe in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61188:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <hi>blood;</hi> and that it is as impoſſible (as was not long agoe obſerved by a learned Judge of this Nation) to <note place="margin">Lord St. <hi>Iohn.</hi>
                  </note> deſtroy the form of the Law, and preſerve the body, as it is to take away the <hi>form</hi> of a man, and to preſerve his <hi>Being</hi>: For when the Law like the Body natural ſhall diſſolve or die, the Juſtice of the Nation, which is as the Soul to that Body, muſt immediately take its flight and be gone.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that would procute the <hi>Vinyard</hi> to be deſtroyed, becauſe they themſelves are ſhut out of it, do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that there are more motions and buſineſs in <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery</hi> diſpatched in one day, than a Committee of the late Parliament did in a year, &amp; more buſineſſe in a year de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined in that and the three other Courts of <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> by themſelves and their miniſterial <hi>Offices,</hi> than all the <hi>Committees</hi> of the late Parliament have diſpatched in 12 years laſt paſt, or would have been able to do after their uſual pace in twice as many more, and need not go far to be informed. What an obſtruction and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance there muſt then be to the people of this Nation, when theſe <hi>Courts</hi> and <hi>Offices</hi> ſhall be taken away, and the People left to attend and Petition for ſome Moneths together, before they can ſo much as get a Petition read, and Tire and Trouble all the Friends they have, for that they might formerly for a far leſſer <hi>Fee,</hi> &amp; in an ordinary courſe have obtained in half an hours ſpace, as ſoon as it was asked for.</p>
               <p>Nor obſerve as they might; that the reaſon why the good intentions of many men in thoſe many ſeveral <hi>Committees</hi> (which the neceſſities of war did cauſe the late Parliament to erect in this Nation) brought them ſo much into the hatred, diſcontents, curſes, &amp; <hi>Complaints</hi> of the People, was (amongſt other their failings) their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61188:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> ignorance in the Laws of the Land, and of the old courſe of expounding, taking-in, and giving out of <hi>reaſon,</hi> their immethodical proceedings, and ſeeking ſometimes to make a reaſon out of half a reaſon, or that which was but a ſhadow or colour of it, which with their many ſcruples (which would not be made by more knowing men) their bidding the people ſo often to withdraw, and adviſing with themſelves, or referring it to their own Counſel (which made many ſeveral hearings of that, which other men would have diſpatched preſently) have been the cauſe of thoſe outeries, pamphletings, and Petitions have from moſt Counties and places been againſt them, and that the horrid delayes and ſmall diſpatch of thoſe Committees (who, if there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe in it, muſt needs in ſo many different opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, arguings, and needleſſe debates amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves be a great deal more redious and undiſpatching, than a fewer number of able men in a <hi>Court</hi>) were much of the cauſe alſo of the peoples heavy complaints againſt the late Parliament.</p>
               <p>And that the <hi>Chancery</hi> and Courts of Juſtice have not for many <hi>hundred</hi> years paſt (put all the Complaints which have been made againſt them together) had ſo many, and ſo univerſal Complaints made againſt them as have in the ſpace of theſe laſt <hi>Ten</hi> years been made againſt the late <hi>Committees,</hi> of which thoſe that have left their <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to the Lawes to cry <hi>Crucifige</hi> would be ill contented if all the Trades in <hi>London</hi> ſhould be at once put down, for that there are greater abuſes in them, Doe not doe as they would be done by, nor think what a drouth and want of Juſtice there will be all over the Land, when the Springs thereof ſhall be ſtopped-up, and what an encreaſe of wants and neceſſities there will
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61188:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> be when the way of preferment, and proviſion for youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Children, ſhall in the ruine of this great <hi>Tribe,</hi> and part of the people, be taken away? And what a ſtrange attempt it would be in <hi>Phyſick</hi> upon the body Natural, to go about to divert the daily and conſtant Courſe of the blood from the heart, and put it into a new way, or to make ſome other parts of the body to do the office of it.</p>
               <p>Nor do thoſe <hi>Propoſers</hi> (who would take away their Neighbours wood to build an <hi>Altar</hi> to ſacrifiſe their own imaginations upon,) conſider, as they ought, what it is to remove the <hi>old Land-mark,</hi> and <hi>enter upon the field of the Fatherleſs;</hi> nor how great a burthen of ſin will lie upon their Souls in the day of <hi>Terror</hi> and <hi>Accompt,</hi> for the unneceſſary ruine of ſo many Thouſand Families, as are now living, and a general diſturbance and diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of a whole Nation, and their poſterity for the time to come, and all upon no greater a Score than their own <hi>preſumption,</hi> and <hi>incapacities</hi> to judge of Laws, and meddle where they had no calling, either from God or Man, and when they ſtop'd their ears like the <hi>Adder,</hi> and might have been <hi>adviſed,</hi> but would not: or how much greater or <hi>ſadder</hi> a burthen it will be to their <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi> if that which they ſhall now fancy to be good, ſhould prove hereafter to be a continual <hi>curſe</hi> and thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to a whole Nation, and a Succeſſion of generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons after them? That the taking away from the people their Courts of Juſtice, and reaſonable Cuſtoms, will not only root out and overturn their <hi>properties,</hi> but caſt it into an <hi>arbitrarineſs</hi> of will and power; from which the beſt intentions and integrity of thoſe, that ſhall be in power at the preſent, will not be able to ſecure the people or their poſterity; And that this ſo great an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61188:10"/> (though carried on with never ſo good purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) may meet with no better a ſucceſs in the end, than that <hi>unadviſed</hi> and loving attempt of old <hi>Pelias</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Poets, who by letting out of the old blood of their <hi>Father,</hi> to procure new, loſt what they might have kept, and gained no more than an impoſſibility to keep him alive, whom they thought to have made young a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
               <p>And that when they ſhall have done all they can, or have obtained what they would of the <hi>Parliament</hi> by ſuch kind of propoſals, it will be to as little ſatisfaction to the people, as to take away (if they could) the <hi>Sun</hi> out of the Firmament, and promiſe them another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of it; or forbid all known experimented Medicines and Courſes in <hi>Phyſick,</hi> and tell them they ſhall have better.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV</hi> That the Lawes are not in themſelves evil, but are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſed by the People.</head>
               <p>ALl which might be ſufficient to call off thoſe <hi>Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> who have no more acquaintance with the Law, than what they got in ſome <hi>Suites</hi> were rightfully adjudged againſt them, and ſome others, who are neer <hi>Allied</hi> unto a buſie ignorance, from troubling the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority with their ſo eager purſute, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of thoſe Laws, which in the beginning of the laſt <hi>Parliament</hi> they took to be the <hi>Walls</hi> and <hi>Bulwarks</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments,</hi> and could proteſt, ſwear, covenant, take arms, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend and hazard their lives and eſtates for to maintain. Or to <hi>perſwade</hi> them not to hunt the <hi>Lamb</hi> inſtead of the <hi>Fox,</hi> or their own happineſs in ſtead of a <hi>grievance,</hi> nor to think their Time well ſpent in Crying-down the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61188:11"/> Fundamental Laws of <hi>England,</hi> without which they once thought they ſhould be moſt miſerable, if they were not hurried, or headlongly driven on by a ſtrange fury of their own <hi>Fancies,</hi> or preſumptions, or an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of ſetting-up themſelves by the ruine and down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall of many Thouſands, will be loſers to every one, will be gainers by it, or were not Acted by ſome <hi>Jeſuiti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cal</hi> party, or influence, would diſturb and deſtroy this Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>To prevent which, and to do what we can as long as there is any hope left, we ſhall intreat them by the Tears and Compaſſion of their <hi>already</hi> too much impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veriſhed, torn, and languiſhing Mother <hi>England,</hi> and the love they ought to bear to their Brethren, and their own (if they will not be carefull of other mens) <hi>poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> to ſtand a little, and look about them, before they drown us and themſelves in that Sea of miſery and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, they are letting in upon us; and either to read our <hi>Lawes,</hi> or be informed by thoſe that underſtand them, and <hi>conſider</hi> well before-hand, now they may help it, that which Truth and a ſad experience may hereafter tel them, when they cannot find a <hi>remedy</hi> for it; That the Laws and Courts of <hi>Juſtice</hi> they world now over-turn, are thoſe Lawes and <hi>Courts,</hi> which by a long-experience, and univerſal <hi>reaſon,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of our Fore-Fathers, have thorough many ages and generations, deſcended and come unto us, as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Birth-right</hi> and Inheritance, will (if rightly exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and inſpected) appear to be <hi>deduced</hi> from no worſe original, or authority, than the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> or <hi>Ten Commandements</hi> themſelves, and the reaſon and equity of many of thoſe other <hi>Laws,</hi> which God himſelf in Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to declare unto the people, That
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61188:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Law of <hi>England</hi> is <hi>Ipſiſsima ratio,</hi> right reaſon it ſelf.</p>
               <p>From which, and the right uſe and practice thereof, if they that ſhall make it their buſineſs to accuſe our Laws and reaſonable <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> and <hi>Courſes,</hi> of Courts of <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſhall but <hi>abſtruct</hi> and take (out of all the <hi>cauſleſs</hi> complaints are made againſt it, which ought to be done by thoſe will judge aright of it) all that happeneth by the ignorance, or weakneſs of men, in making of their <hi>Contracts</hi> and Aſſurances one with another; The cavils, and ſtrange ſubtilties, of thoſe that would deceive, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, or take <hi>advantage</hi> by it; The making of <hi>Wills</hi> and <hi>Conveyances</hi> by ignorant perſons, unfit placing of words in them, and want of coherence, or ſignification, (which do not ſeldom beget contradictions, or perplexities of the ſenſe or meaning of the parties) their holding hard to advantages gotten; by a miſtake of words or parties to create a right, or title, where there ſhould be none; Wreſting of Laws to their own purpoſes; Self-concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, falſe or frivolous Suggeſtions, in their motions, or deſires to the <hi>Courts; Reiteration</hi> and ſucceſſion of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and ſtrange allegations, not at firſt diſcernable by the <hi>Lawyers</hi> or <hi>Judges</hi> themſelves; Haſty, and wilfull commencing of <hi>Suites</hi> upon ſmall or no advice at all; <hi>Ravelling</hi> and perplexing of their own Cauſes, Eluding, or ſtriving to over-reach the Laws, or ſtrain them beyond their intentions; Ignorance or wilfulneſſe in managing of their Cauſes, and the frowardneſs or unquietneſs of their own <hi>ſpirits,</hi> in courſing one another, through all the Courts of <hi>Law</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall, by ſeverall Tryals, and Verdicts, bringing writs of <hi>Error</hi> upon them, out of the <hi>Common Pleas</hi> into the <hi>Vpper Bench,</hi> thence to the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer</hi> Chamber, to be heard by all the Judges of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:61188:12"/> Thence to the Parliament, (though they pay great and ſeveral coſts to their adverſaries) diſcontinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of writs of <hi>Error,</hi> or abatement of them, by the death, or inſtance of ſome of the parties, bringing their Bills, and Croſſe <hi>Bills</hi> in <hi>Chancery,</hi> getting <hi>Orders</hi> upon Orders, Decrees upon <hi>Decrees, Rehearings, Reviews,</hi> or Diſmiſſions, Entitling the State afterwards to what they ſued or vexed one another for; Appeals from the Country-<hi>Committees,</hi> to <hi>Haberdaſhers Hall,</hi> from thence to the <hi>Committee</hi> of <hi>Indempnity,</hi> Thence to the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of <hi>Obſtructions,</hi> from thence to the Committee of <hi>Petitions</hi> for grievances, And from thence to the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> again, and if they be rejected, or cannot be heard in one <hi>Parliament,</hi> Try another, and another, and as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as they can live to ſollicite; their multiplying of needleſſe and frivolous Actions, obſtinate, and will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full endeavours, in trying all they can to overpower, or woorie their Adverſaries, never acquieſcing in the Judgement of their own <hi>Lawiers</hi> or of any <hi>Court,</hi> as long as any wit, or invention of any other <hi>Lawier</hi> (who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alwayes ſee through his <hi>Clients</hi> unjuſt pretences) can but ſhew them the way to further vexations; The Neceſſity which lies upon Judges and Courts to keep Rules &amp; Orders, which may not be broken to help par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Caſes; <hi>Miſcarriage</hi> of Cauſes by miſpleadings, &amp; <hi>Incertainties</hi> in the Plaintiffs or Defendants own Actions or <hi>inſtructions;</hi> Their hiding or concealing <hi>truths,</hi> Their not agreeing or right Stating of matters of fact, miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of good Laws &amp; remedies to ill purpoſes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit &amp; delay of one another in references, weakneſſe of <hi>Arbitrators,</hi> and <hi>Awards,</hi> deceit or ignorance of <hi>Sollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> (a race of people was not allowed or heard of in the Law about 100 years agoe, (but where No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61188:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> had and reteined them in their houſes as me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial ſervants) too many of which of late have been bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and buſie <hi>Trades</hi>-men, or ſuch as ſcarcely know the names of a book of <hi>law,</hi> or to ſpell, write, or read. Their champerty <hi>maintenance</hi> and <hi>ambodextry</hi> (ſome knowing and honeſt <hi>Sollicitors</hi> excepted) taking mony before hand of their Clients, and never giving an Accompt for it, <hi>miſtakings</hi> or wilfulneſſe of <hi>Juries,</hi> want of eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, intricacy of cauſes, Errors or miſinterpretation as miſtake the of Judges, Ignorance, malice or ſelf ends of thoſe that ſpeak ill of them, and the difficulties which ſometimes do lie upon the wiſeſt and moſt honeſt of men in diſcerning between truth and falſhood, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding betwixt them, and diſtinguiſh, as our Fore-Fathers and the wiſdome of former ages uſed to do, betwixt the right uſe, and the abuſe of them, between particular miſchiefs, and general <hi>inconveniences,</hi> betwixt the Inconveniences which ſome one Law may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times bring upon a few particular men, and the good it brings to one hundred thouſand others at the ſame time, and allow but (that which was never yet denyed to all the <hi>Lawes</hi> of the world) an <hi>impoſsibility</hi> of foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, preventing or remedying of all things which the wickedneſſe of the hearts of men, or their devices may lay in their way, there will not be enough left to prove them to be corrupt in their foundations.</p>
               <p>Take away and lay at the <hi>doors</hi> of thoſe that ought to bear it, the ſelling or mortgaging of lands Twice or Thrice over, the Counterfeiting and putting to the Seals and hands of parties and witneſſes, <hi>forgeries,</hi> and taking out, and putting in of words into deeds or evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, ſtrange and unheard-of <hi>combinations,</hi> practices, <hi>Witchcrafts</hi> and <hi>Sorceries,</hi> putting of <hi>dead</hi> mens hands to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61188:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> Wills, moulding, hiring of falſe witneſſes, and Suborning or packing or laying of <hi>Iuries</hi> (which are the Actions of the parties themſelves to compaſſe and bring to paſſe their own wicked purpoſes, and not of the <hi>Lawiers.</hi>)</p>
               <p>Let it be but conſidered, that if there happen in an age ſome unreconcilable Suits, wherein ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious ſpirits have for many years together, chaſed and vexed one another out of one Action into another, almoſt to their utter undoing, There have been in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very year of thoſe many years, many thouſands of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (as may be demonſtrated to any that will call for a proof of it) diſpatched &amp; put to an end by the Courts of Law at <hi>Weſtninſter,</hi> or in the Circuits, &amp; that a multitude of People Actions and buſineſſes more than formerly, in a Time of more Deceit, Falſhood, Perjuries, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and cunning combinations, and breaches of Truſt, than ever were, may make an increaſe &amp; multiplicity of Suits, and yet the Lawiers, who in an age have not a common Barretor amongſt them, be as innocent as the Phyſicians, who are not accuſed for much practiſe in a time of Peſtilence, or when there are ſtore of <hi>Epidemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> diſeaſes, there will be no cauſe to ſay that the Law is endleſſe.</p>
               <p>Let it be but conſidered, that the greater part of eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed <hi>Fees</hi> in the Courts of juſtice, are leſſe than what the moſt common <hi>Artificers</hi> do take for their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and as for any which exceed that rate, are but that which was allowed one <hi>Hundred</hi> years agoe, when the rate and price of Cloths and Victuals was not one in three ſo much as it is now; that the <hi>Attorneys</hi> 3 s. 4 d. fee, and the Lawiers 10 s. fee, would then have bought 3 times more than what may be now for it.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:61188:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>That the <hi>Gentry</hi> have ſince raiſed their rents two parts in <hi>Three,</hi> the Farmers the price of their Corn and Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, and the Citizens their Commodities, and ſervants and workmen raiſed their wages, yet the Lawiers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſome eminent and great <hi>practiſers,</hi> who take but the Free will offering of thoſe that give them the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Fees, to take the greater care of their buſineſſe, have but the ſame Fees were formerly taken by them.</p>
               <p>That the Lawiers who had no worſe a name aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently given to their profeſſion by the moſt Civilized Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> than <hi>Sacerdotes justttiae,</hi> the Miniſters of Juſtice, and had ſo right an eſteem in our former Parliaments, as by ſeveral Acts of Parliament made upon ſeveral and ſucceſſive neceſſities of the People, in 2 <hi>Edward 3 cap. 2. 14. Edward 3 cap. 16. 34. Edward 3. cap. 1.</hi> and <hi>20. Richard 2. cap. 10.</hi> It was ſpecially provided, that none but men learned in the Law ſhould be made <hi>Juſtices</hi> of <hi>Aſsize</hi> and <hi>Goal</hi> delivery, and that there ſhould be in every County men learned in the <hi>Law</hi> made Juſtices of the peace; And in all their Actions either at home in their Counties, or at <hi>London</hi> in the Terms, are known to be men of Godlineſſe, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, and learning, and compared with any other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion or part of the People, to have fewer men of vice or ignominie amongſt them than any other profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Let it be but conſidered that the Law (as it may be demonſtrated, if an accompt were kept, as ſome Phyſitians do of their conſultations and Cures, or as the People of the <hi>Bath</hi> do of ſome that are cured in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very year) doth in every year recover and get in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Thouſands of men <hi>debts</hi> redreſſe their <hi>Injuries,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their <hi>rights,</hi> ſecure their <hi>eſtates,</hi> reſcue and take ſome <hi>Innocent</hi> mens lives and eſtates out of the jawes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61188:14"/> of death or oppreſſion, ſupport the hand of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and is as <hi>eyes</hi> and <hi>ears</hi> unto it, puts her Judgement in the <hi>right</hi> way when it was ſometimes allmoſt carried off, ormiſlead into a <hi>wrong,</hi> and hath kept us and our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers in a greater ſafety &amp; certainty of it than <hi>Roman Legions</hi> could have done, and Ten greatet <hi>Armyes</hi> than we now bear the charge of.</p>
               <p>That in the determination or adjudging of every Action or Suit in Law or Equity, one of the parties is diſcontented, and one of them moſt commonly faulty, or much miſtaken in the grounds of that Conteſt (A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Debt or of other natures, where the Plaintiff will not give time, and the Defendant only ſtands out a Suit to gain it only excepted) and do all they can to lay the fault upon the Law, when it ſhould be charged upon themſelves.</p>
               <p>And that the difficulty in the caſe before <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> betwixt the true Mother of the Child, and the falſe, could not be charged upon any defects of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Laws, or the Profeſſors thereof, but the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and falſe pretences of her that had no right to it, and that every diſcontent and every Complaint is not juſt becauſe the partie thinks it to be ſo; There will be as little cauſe to ſay that the practice of the Law, as to the <hi>Law</hi> it ſelf, or to the <hi>Lawiers,</hi> is a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, or that they are worſe than Ten Thouſand <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils,</hi> as that <hi>Tenterden</hi> Steeple is the cauſe of <hi>Goodwyne</hi> Sands: For moſt of the things complained of in the Law (if impartially and knowingly examined) will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be neither from the <hi>Law,</hi> or by the Law it <hi>Self,</hi> or of the <hi>Eſſence,</hi> Nature, or <hi>Intention</hi> of it, but meerly proceeding from the people, and their own miſuſe or abuſe of them, which being not evill in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61188:14"/> but commanding good things to be done, and forbidding evil, are no more to be charged with the faults which the people themſelves Commit in abuſing of them, than that great <hi>Luminary</hi> and comfort of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind the <hi>Sun,</hi> can be ſaid to be the cauſe of darkneſſe, or ill influences, becauſe in his journey or execution of his Office he is ſometimes orecharg'd with Foggs, ill va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, or exhalations from the Earth, which he would diſperſe or carry away, or meets with ſo many Clouds, interpoſitions, and Shadows of the Earth, Conjunctions of <hi>Planets,</hi> or Malevolent <hi>Aſpects;</hi> than the neceſſary arts of Phyſick and Chirurgery are to be blamed for the many Errors and miſchiefs are done by <hi>Montebanks,</hi> or confident and credulous women that have no skill in them; than wine and women for the General abuſes of them, or Religion and the Sacred Scriptures, becauſe the world hath of late been troubled with ſo many He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies and Schiſms, proceeding from the miſ-interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the one, and practice of the other, and may the better be underſtood and believed to be thus <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> when thoſe that not long agoe could run to <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> and cry for juſtice againſt the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Strafford,</hi> but for at moſt an endeavour to ſubvert the Laws, and cryed out they could have no Trading or ſubſiſtence, if his head were not taken off, cannot now give us a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why thoſe very Laws, and the Courts that admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred them, ſhould not now be as good as they were then.</p>
               <p>Or why the Old <hi>Chancery</hi> and <hi>Court</hi> hands, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made out of <hi>Saxon</hi> letters or Characters before any <hi>Friers</hi> or <hi>Monks</hi> ever came into <hi>England,</hi> have through ſo many generations come down to us, and given ſuch a legibility, duration, and continuance to all our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61188:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> as they may yet be plainly ſeen and read for 7 or 8 hundred years paſt, ſhould be more inconvenient, Popiſh, &amp; Antichriſtian, than the Secretary, &amp; other Mungrel and Scrible daſhed hands made out of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and Italian, which will not as it begins to appear already laſt 7 years together.</p>
               <p>Or why the Lawiers may not uſe <hi>Abbreviations</hi> as well as the <hi>Doctors</hi> &amp; <hi>Apothecaries,</hi> or why <hi>Abbreviations</hi> ſhould be bad &amp; not allowable in Court or Chancery hands or writing, as well as in the writings which Merchants have daily occaſion to uſe, in the <hi>Dutch, French,</hi> or <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Laws or writings: Or why the Law ſhould be bad becauſe the Lawiers doe uſe Terms of Art or ſhort expreſſions tending much to the eaſe of themſelves, and the Court and Judges that are to hear them are not denyed to all other Arts and Sciences, but are to Brick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layers and Carpenters, to Farriers who have their Terms of their own making, as to cure the <hi>Mallender, Farſes, Trunchions, Bards</hi> and <hi>Wanders</hi> in a horſe, and to heal a wound in the <hi>Lampas,</hi> and to the Seamen or Mariners who are never found fault with for uſing the Tearms of <hi>Starboard,</hi> and <hi>Larboard, Lee ſhore, Miſne-Maſt,</hi> ſhrouds, bear up, <hi>Weather-gage,</hi> run ſo many glaſſes, and the like ſtrange words and notions are not to be underſtood by any but thoſe that have ſerved long at the profeſſion, and learned their Sea <hi>Grammar.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it will be time to tell thoſe that ſhall thus labour to take away from the Nation their well-being by ſuch their fond propoſals, That the war to which they contributed was not undertaken by the late Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to pull down the fundamental Laws, but to preſerve them, and that if the <hi>Articles</hi> or Publick Faith but once given by the <hi>Army</hi> to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61188:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> Enemies upon the ſurrender of <hi>Oxford</hi> and other <hi>Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> were ſo precious and ſacred to the late Parliament and <hi>Army,</hi> as well as it is to this, as not in the leaſt part to be violated, Thoſe many great proteſtations of the late Parliament and Army in very many of their Declarations and Remonſtrances (ſome whereof were ordered to be read in <hi>Churches</hi>) and their Publick Faith ſo many times reiterated and given, may ſurely give a ſtop and denyal to theſe <hi>Traders</hi> in <hi>Innovation,</hi> eſpecially when it ſhall be conſidered, that thoſe Publick Faiths and promiſes, were not made or given to thoſe that were Enemies and fought againſt them, as the other ſide did in a jealouſie, and diſtruſt that they did not intend (as they promiſed, to maintain thoſe Laws, which they pretended to fight for; but to thoſe that believing them did adventure and engage all they had, and went all the way along with them; and that if there were nothing elſe to be ſaid for it, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their great and continual care of the People and Commonwealth will not certainly ſuffer the Chancery and all the Courts of Juſtice which depend upon it to be taken away, would be ſo much againſt the former Cuſtoms and reaſon of this as well as other Nations, as it is not be precedented, but will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:61188:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> That to put down or take away the <hi>Chancery,</hi> and ſo many Courts of Juſtice which depend upon it, will be ſo much againſt the former <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> or <hi>reaſon</hi> of or any other <hi>Nation,</hi> as it is not to be precedented.</head>
               <p>TO what was done by the <hi>Athenians,</hi> who in all their <hi>Oſtraciſmes,</hi> and popular <hi>unquietneſſe,</hi> could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their Laws and Courts of Juſtice. Or the <hi>Romans,</hi> who in all their Changings and <hi>Tumblings</hi> from one go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to another, in their ſending for new Laws to <hi>Athens,</hi> their complaints and diſlike of Magiſtrates.</p>
               <p>Bloody proſcriptions of the <hi>Sullan</hi> and <hi>Marian</hi> facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; <hi>Tribunitial</hi> powers, <hi>Dictatorſhips,</hi> and revolving back again into <hi>Monarchy,</hi> could keep cloſe to the body of their Laws and Conſtitutions.</p>
               <p>To what our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> did in his reformation, who when he brought the glad Tidings of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> into the world, took away the rigor and <hi>Ceremonial</hi> part of <note place="margin">Hiſt. Juris Civil. compoſit per Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianum</note> the Law without deſtroying the <hi>moral.</hi> To the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiof the <hi>Civil Laws</hi> by <hi>Juſtinian</hi> the <hi>Emperour,</hi> who having appointed <hi>Ten</hi> of the moſt eminent and worthy of his <hi>Empire,</hi> (amongſt which were <hi>Tribonianus</hi> and diverſe learned profeſſors of the <hi>Laws,</hi>) to read over and peruſe all the voluminous Laws in being, did compile and make out of them his <hi>Pandects,</hi> and that body of the <hi>Civil Law</hi> which hath for above one <hi>Thouſand</hi> years ſince inhabited and been eſteemed amongſt the moſt Civilized Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> as a great part of their <note place="margin">Chronic. <hi>Jo. Erom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi>
                  </note> guide and reaſon;</p>
               <p>Contrary to what our old King <hi>Alured</hi> or <hi>Alfred</hi> did
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61188:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> about 800 years ſince, who could in Parliament reform ſome of the <hi>Laws</hi> made by King <hi>Ethelbert</hi> above 200 years before, puniſh ſome Judges, and think ne ver the worſe of the <hi>Laws,</hi> for ſome abuſe of them.</p>
               <p>To what <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Comquerour</hi> did, who by gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <note place="margin">Chronic. Leichfiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſe, &amp; in 2 Edw. Confeſso<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, confirm. per Guli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elm. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</note> the <hi>Saxons</hi> their old Laws (many of which are ſtill amongſt us) ſtrengthned his Conqueſts, and gave quiet entertainment to as many of his own e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts, and <hi>Norman</hi> Cuſtoms, as were found to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable.</p>
               <p>To that of his Son <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>firſt,</hi> Who could amend ſome of his Fathers and predeceſſors Laws, without overturning all the reſt.</p>
               <p>To that of <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>ſecond,</hi> Who removed and alterd many things amiſſe in the execution of Laws, but left that which was good and uſefull in them.</p>
               <p>To what was done by <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>firſt,</hi> Who fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all his <hi>Judges</hi> but Two, ſo corrupt as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved puniſhments, did not baniſh all the Laws with them.</p>
               <p>To what was done by <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>eighth,</hi> Who in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation <note place="margin">Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones legum Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtic. &amp; in Epiſt. H. 8. &amp; E. 6.</note> of the Eccleſiaſtical Laws, appointed by Act of Parliament in 35 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. to be done by eight <hi>Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> eight <hi>Canon,</hi> eight <hi>Civil,</hi> and eight <hi>Common</hi> Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers; And by his moſt vertuous Son <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>ſixth</hi> delegated to that learned &amp; Godly <hi>Martyr Thomas Cramner</hi> Arch Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury, Peter Martyr,</hi> &amp; other Divines, 2 Doctors of the <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Canon</hi> Laws, and two Common Lawiers, did leave what was good to remain of it.</p>
               <p>Contrary to what the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61188:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> Provinces did, who in their imbittered deteſt of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> government, could find it as neceſſary as reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to keep their <hi>Common Law, Burgundian</hi> and <hi>Batavian</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cornel. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ostad. in Epiſt. lib. de Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione feudi Juris ſcript. Hollandiae.</note> cuſtoms, the Fewdal Laws of the <hi>Lombards,</hi> and as much of the <hi>Roman</hi> and Civil Laws, as did not contradict their own, &amp; therfore in the laying of the foundation of their confederacy and government did in one of the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of their ſolemn league made at <hi>Virecht</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1579. bind one another to the defence of their Laws and Statutes, <hi>a Majoribus accepta,</hi> and ordered the People <note place="margin">In Foedere Ultralect Anno 1579 Art. 2. &amp; 21.</note> to be ſworn unto them. To the Wiſdom and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of our forefathers in <hi>Parliaments,</hi> who (if ſome of them had been fooliſh, could not for the Major part in every Parliament been have deſtitute of wiſdom; or if in one year, meeting, time, age, or generation, cannot with the reputation of wiſdom to any that ſhall ſo judge of them, be thought to have been ſo to a continual ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) did only correct, alter, and add, as there were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities or occaſions, but left us our Laws and reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cuſtoms to preſerve our eſtates and properties.</p>
               <p>Contrary to all the Petitions and pretences of Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, that ever were exhibited by any of the people before, or ſince the Conqueſt, to any <hi>King, Parliament,</hi> great <hi>Councel,</hi> or <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> for above one thouſand years.</p>
               <p>To what our <hi>Aunceſtors</hi> did in <hi>England,</hi> Who in the change of governments, and ſucceſſion of Kings, from the <hi>Saxons</hi> to the <hi>Danes,</hi> from them to the <hi>Normans,</hi> thence to the <hi>Plantagenet</hi> line, from the <hi>right</hi> Heirs to the <hi>wrong,</hi> from the <hi>red roſe</hi> to the <hi>white,</hi> from the <hi>white</hi> to the <hi>red</hi> and <hi>white</hi> united in <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>ſeventh,</hi> from the <hi>Catholick</hi> religion to the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> from that to the <hi>Catholick,</hi> and from that back again to the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:61188:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> line to the <hi>Scottiſh,</hi> did never find any cauſe to take away that <hi>Court,</hi> which they found by ſo long and ſucceſſive experiments to be the conſervator of Juſtice.</p>
               <p>Contrary to the <hi>National Covenant,</hi> which many have endeavoured to prove to be conſiſtent with the Ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; to what was done by the late Parliament in their reformation of religion, wherein, though the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and Book of <hi>Common Prayer</hi> were put down and aboliſhed (and that not at once) did not put down all the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Church,</hi> or all the Diſcipline, or parts of it, nor ſhut up the <hi>Church</hi> doors.</p>
               <p>Contrary to the many <hi>Declarations</hi> vows and <hi>Imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of the late <hi>Parliament.</hi> The many Declarations and Remonſtrances of the <hi>Army.</hi> The Courſe held in the late Conqueſts of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> who by enjoying their <hi>Lawes</hi> and Courts of Juſtice have yeelded an eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſubmiſſion to it. The Act of the late <hi>Parliament</hi> in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> which declared and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to the people that they would not alter, nor take away the fundamental <hi>Lawes.</hi> The Peoples pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of their ingagement upon it. The Act or order of <hi>Parliament</hi> for the regulation of the <hi>Lawes.</hi> The <hi>regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators Syſteme,</hi> and the Nature of a <hi>reformation</hi> or regulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The late Act for taking away <hi>Fines</hi> in <hi>Chancery,</hi> and many of the Petitions that of late have been againſt the Lawes, which deſired a <hi>regulation,</hi> but not a total taking of them away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:61188:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> That the very Being of Parliaments is preſerved by the <hi>Laws,</hi> and that ſo great a diſtemper and diſturbance as will come upon the people by putting down of the <hi>Laws,</hi> will by a neceſsitie of Juſtice, and of the better ordering of <hi>Affairs,</hi> bring them back again by a revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of time into their old Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel.</head>
               <p>WHich for ſo much of them as have their <hi>Principles</hi> from the Laws of <hi>Nature</hi> and right <hi>reaſon,</hi> and the conſent of them, or are founded and deduced from them, are ſo interwoven and radicated in the very Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Parliaments, ſo <hi>inſeparable</hi> from it, and ſo <hi>recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> to it, as that high Court of Parliament, which is not by themſelves intended to be any ſtanding or ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Court</hi> or Rule of Juſtice, cannot when it ſhall ſit upon emergencies or matters of greater conſequence, be without it, no more than the people can in the <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals</hi> or abſence of it, for that the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> which God <hi>imprinted</hi> and put into the Hearts of all Mankind, and that Law of <hi>reaſon,</hi> which bindeth Creatures reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in this world, and with which by Reaſon they moſt plainly perceive themſelves to be bound, and ſo much of our Laws, which out of the Law either of God, or Nature, or Reaſon, our Forefathers probably gathered and conceived to be expedient (which the learned <hi>Hooker</hi> putting all together calleth the ſecond <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hooker 1 lib.</hi> Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Pollicy</note> Law <hi>eternal</hi>) are ſo in ſome ſort immutable, as they cannot be taken away, or repealed by any Act of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament whatſoever, but will retorn and grow up again with the nature and reaſon of <hi>Mankind;</hi> for Laws of men,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61188:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> not contrary to the Law of God, nor to the Law of <hi>reaſon,</hi> are to be obſerved in the Law of the <hi>Soul</hi> and <note place="margin">Doctor and Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient 4 Chap.</note> he that deſpiſeth them reſiſteth <hi>God,</hi> and that which plain and neceſſary reaſon bindeth men unto, will upon ſome inconvenience or neceſſity, at one time or other, get it ſelf in again, and obtain an allowance or ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of human Laws for it.</p>
               <p>Which ſhould adviſe a great inſpection, and <hi>exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> into the <hi>nature, cauſe,</hi> and effect of all our <hi>Laws,</hi> before a ſentence of <hi>condemnation</hi> paſſe againſt them, that ſo it may be clearly known, what, and how much of them have their Being from the Law of <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> right reaſon, or convenience, and a value accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly put upon them, that the <hi>Gold</hi> may not be caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for the droſſe, nor the <hi>Saint</hi> for his infirmity; That we may not be ſent to ſeek after in the rubbidg for that we might have kept, or laid by, or not ſeem to have pullen down all the houſe, when ſome little part of it would have ſerved the turn, or to be ſuch ill Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, as to caſt away the materials might have ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for the new building, and is better or more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial than any can be gotten inſtead of it, of which opinion were all our former <hi>Parliaments,</hi> who hitherto in their correcting and altering of Laws, could never be brought to forſake any thing might be good, or fit to <note place="margin">Sir <hi>Francis Bacon.</hi> Judge <hi>Hutton</hi> in his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſhip mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and Lord <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bart</hi> in his Reports.</note> remain of them, and all our Forefathers, who in their greateſt eſteem and reverence of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that an Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> it ſelf, enacting any thing againſt Common <hi>right,</hi> and right <hi>reaſon,</hi> would be void, and of none effect; to what end then ſhould theſe men ſollicite a Parliament, to take away the matter of its own form and ſubſiſtence, and its Being or <hi>coexistence</hi> with the Laws, or to take away that which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61188:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> is to be a rule of juſtice to the people, when they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not themſelves intend it, or to lay by thoſe Laws which the wiſdom of their <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> thought they had done the people good ſervice when they did procure them to be enacted, and thoſe reaſonable cuſtomes which the people were wont to ſwear their <hi>Kings</hi> to obſerve, when the late Parliament took it to be a good way for the preſervation of the Laws and Liberties of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that <hi>Sheriffs</hi> and Juſtices ſhould be ſworn to the <note place="margin">Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance <hi>15 De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember 1641.</hi> and 26 of <hi>May 1642.</hi>
                  </note> due execution of the petition of <hi>right (m)</hi> Stiled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the <hi>Conſervatory</hi> of Lawes, took Arms for the maintenance therof, &amp; appealed to the people touching that <hi>imputation</hi> (which they ſaid was then laid upon them) that they which repreſented all the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> and had ſo great a ſhare in it, ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to take away the <hi>Laws,</hi> and run ſo great a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard to make themſelves Slaves.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, if the Parliament (to pleaſe theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet and propoſing ſpirits, and let them ſee what is to ask <hi>Stones</hi> inſtead of <hi>Bread,</hi> or <hi>Serpents</hi> inſtead of <hi>Fiſhes</hi>) ſhould give them the <hi>miſery</hi> which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of them, and contribute (which cannot be eaſily imagined) ſo much to their unruly deſires, as to let them fling off their old <hi>Laws,</hi> like an unuſefull, or too long a worn garment; It will be no hard matter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of <hi>Lilly,</hi> and his College of <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> to foreſee (what, beſides the many miſchiefs and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences before recited, muſt be endured and gone through in the interim) and foretell what will become of it; for ſuppoſe it to be done, and that we ſee the old man put into his Cradle again, or <hi>Adam</hi> into his Apron of fig-leaves, the event will come up as cloſe as a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion to good Premiſes, that ſuch young Committees
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61188:19"/> or new model <hi>Courts</hi> will in time creep into the method and manner of the <hi>old;</hi> all that was reaſon in one caſe or cauſe will be made uſe of, and made a <hi>precedent</hi> in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: The wiſer and moſt able men will be followed, pleadings and allegations will be by the Committee or Judges themſelves ordered to be with Certainties or Method; The Court or Committee will more willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hear thoſe that can ſave them a labour, by ſpeaking more ſhort and pertinently, than the parties themſelves, and the parties themſelves will rather deſire men of skill, and ſuch as know the uſage and orders of the <hi>Courts</hi> and <hi>Committees,</hi> to ſpeak for them, than to adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to do it themſelves, when their intereſt may beget a paſſion and diſturbance, and hinder them from the right managing and ordering of their own buſineſſe, abuſes and miſdoings of thoſe that attend thoſe Courts or Committees will from time to time require new or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and officers to prevent them. For in this, manner, in all probabilitie, and without doubt, thoſe moſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable and uſefull Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> came by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees and ſmall beginnings, through the Courſe and care of ſo many ages to the perfection is now to be ſeen in them, cannot be denied by thoſe that ſhall without the Spectacles of ignorance or partiallity, but equally and judiciouſly look upon them.</p>
               <p>But if any ſhall doubt of this neceſſity of the Laws falling again into their own <hi>Chanel,</hi> after a Series or long courſe of inconveniences to the people, and ſome ages ſpent in bewailing the loſſe of their former happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; Let them ſee but what hath been done but in three or four years ſpace in the Committee of <hi>Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> at <hi>Haberdaſhers</hi> Hall, who from a Committee of ſeven Commiſſioners, with a Clark or Regiſter to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61188:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> them, can now uſe the benefit of a Bar to admit Lawiers and ſuch as know the uſe of their Committee to plead before them, order ſome things to be done by the Clarks and officers in an ordinary Courſe, and other things not to order, and have the uſe of an <hi>Examiner, Remembrancer,</hi> and <hi>Aſsiſtant, Counſel</hi> of the Court, can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer cauſes, have an <hi>Auditor,</hi> an <hi>Attorney,</hi> or <hi>Sollicitor</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, mark, ſign, and ſeal, their <hi>orders</hi> or <hi>warrants</hi> whereby they may not be counterfeited, order men to take Copies of their own Petitions, and leave the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginals, to file <hi>affidavits</hi> and <hi>reports,</hi> and that none ſhall be heard without bringing the laſt <hi>order,</hi> or a Copie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of under the Regiſters hands; Turn the way of Petitions as is now lately done into a way of Motions, have under-<hi>Clarks</hi> in ſeveral diſtributions of imployment, <hi>Door<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keepers, Meſſengers</hi> or <hi>Serjeants,</hi> to commit and impriſon men for not obeying their orders; order and allow of <hi>Fees</hi> to be taken by their <hi>Officers,</hi> appoint certain days and times for ſeveral ſorts of buſineſſe, and have their vacations or <hi>intermiſsions,</hi> in which Committee or Court now a breeding, although every man hath a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of pleading or ſpeaking in his own cauſe, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he that was never there before, may hurt, or miſchief, or perplex his own buſineſſe, or go a longer way about, for want of the knowledge of the ways or <hi>courſes</hi> there holden, or what is fit to be asked, or is uſually, or ordinarily granted, moſt men that have to do with them, are ſo unwilling to be without the help of <hi>Lawiers,</hi> or thoſe that can inſtruct them, as they make uſe of <hi>Sollicitors,</hi> and thoſe that are not <hi>Lawiers,</hi> to move and plead for them, inſomuch as little Mr. <hi>Kirk</hi> formerly a Clark of the Committee of the imdempnity, and Captain <hi>Smith</hi> formerly a <hi>Tradeſman,</hi> do conſtantly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61188:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> appear and plead at that Bar in their black Caps, with great bundles of <hi>Breviars</hi> and papers, as if they were grave profeſſors and <hi>Serjeants</hi> at Law; So as it may be ringhtly enough concluded, that until there ſhall be (which God forbid) a prohibition againſt all <hi>reaſon,</hi> the Laws which are but right reaſon, cannot be total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken away, or if they ſhall receive a change from the old right way of reaſon, to a new and round about way of it, there will be a neceſſity of making uſe of them again for the people, and the reaſon that hath heretofore guided them, can no more be kept from the ſame paths they have <hi>troad</hi> in all this while, or ſome other made very near, or like unto them, than they will be from all manner of reaſoning, or uſe of their natural <hi>Logick,</hi> though the art of <hi>Logick</hi> ſhould be forbidden to be uſed, or the uſe of medicines, though that moſt neceſſary art and profeſſion of <hi>Phyſick</hi> be baniſhed out of this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> for which, they that ſhall thus propoſe the caſting away of the old Laws, and Rules of reaſon, will at the beſt get no more thanks of the <hi>Major</hi> part of the people, than a <hi>Phyſician</hi> ſhall have of his patient, for putting him out of a competency of health, into an abſolute ſickneſſe, and leave him after many years troubleſome courſe of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> and dyet, to find his way (if he can) again into his former condition.</p>
               <p>But leſt theſe that thus trouble themſelves to bring trouble upon a whole Nation, as well as themſelves, ſhould ſo over-<hi>eſteem</hi> that which they intend to put in the room of our good old Laws, and Cuſtomes, as to think no loſſe or ruine ſo great, but may be recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by what they offer inſtead of it; It will not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe to examine by the rule of right reaſon, and what
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61188:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> hath happened formerly, and what is like to come by ſuch propoſals (if they ſhould be granted) and how far thoſe kind of new ways may amount to a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of the Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> That the erecting of ſo many new <hi>Courts,</hi> as are propoſed, or the cutting and tranſlating the great <hi>Courts</hi> at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> into ſo many little <hi>Juriſdictions,</hi> will (beſides the before-mentioned <hi>Inconveniences)</hi> not only be very prejudicial to the <hi>State,</hi> but to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>cantoning</hi> or cutting of the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall into ſo many <hi>County</hi> Courts, or parts (as ſome have propoſed) will if there ſhould be but a ſtanding Court in every <hi>County,</hi> (except <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middleſex</hi>) make almoſt as many great <hi>Courts</hi> in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> (beſides thoſe carkaſes of Courts, which ſome are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to leave at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to determine <hi>Appeals,</hi> and other neceſſaries to that <hi>contrivement</hi>) as there will be <hi>Counties,</hi> the yearly allowance or Salarie of whoſe <hi>Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> if they ſhould have but two <hi>hundred</hi> pound <hi>per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> for every <hi>Judge,</hi> according to the number of <hi>Five</hi> in every <hi>County</hi> Court of <hi>Fifty,</hi> will amount to 50000 l. <hi>per Annum</hi> more charges than the Commonwealth is at already for <hi>Judges</hi> Salaries.</p>
               <p>And when they ſhall be thus paid and furniſhed out, will (if Lawiers ſhall be ſo much <hi>excluded</hi> from being Judges as hath been propoſed) be as to Four in every Five of them, meer Strangers to the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land, or know ſo little of them, as not to be relyed upon for their Judgements: For we cannot ſuppoſe that the eleven
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61188:21"/> 
                  <hi>Judges</hi> in the Courts at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall are intended to be any of them, or can be at one and the ſame time at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and in theſe new County <hi>Courts,</hi> or ſerve, or be enough to make one, in every of theſe Fifty County <hi>Courts,</hi> as ſome would contrive it, to ſit with theſe new County Judges, who having (as is to be feared) not read much of men, or books, will have no ground or capacity for knowledge to grow in, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of parts or <hi>learning</hi> to build up an <hi>ability</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but be willfull, or obſtinate in their ways or opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for want of better underſtanding, or domineering, becauſe they ſhall not be able to know when they do <hi>well</hi> or <hi>ill.</hi> And if they ſhould be <hi>honeſt</hi> (which perhaps will not alwayes happen) their want of knowledge of the Laws, and the rules they ſhould go by; their not knowing how to underſtand what ſhall be ſaid to them, nor what anſwers to give; their inability to expound the Law by other Laws, or make a right conſtruction of the words or meaning of Deeds or Parties, or to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh and divide betwixt <hi>truth</hi> and falſhood, <hi>right</hi> and wrong, reaſon and pretences of it, colour or reality, or how to find the difference betwixt the Caſes or <hi>Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences</hi> that ſhall be urged by the one ſide or the other, or to ſtate the matter of Fact, or to ſever the point or material part from the circumſtances, will make them as fruitfull in their oppreſſion as in their <hi>errors,</hi> and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, apt to be <hi>led</hi> or <hi>miſlead</hi> by their fellow <hi>Judges</hi> that ſhall be Lawiers, or (which will be worſe) to be like <hi>wax</hi> taking the impreſſion of every mans <hi>Seal</hi> that ſhall be laſt clapt upon them; be directed by a <hi>Wife,</hi> or <hi>Clerk,</hi> or ſome other ſimple or knaviſh <hi>favourite,</hi> that ſhall broak and trade in every cauſe that ſhall come before them, and be ſure to abuſe it.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:61188:22"/>
               <p>Trouble and delay the people with needleſſe ſcruples and niceties, by making <hi>Quaeries</hi> or doubts of that, which to others would be common and eaſie, and ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling at every word that comes not up to their <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions,</hi> give advantage to knaves, and put men to ſeek indirect Courſes or ways to ballance the <hi>Judges,</hi> becauſe they dare not truſt them to do that which they ought to do; hurt rather, than help ſuch as ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and oppreſſed, or are not allowed. Counſel to plead for them, make them be ready to allow of all the reaſons given by the Plaintiffs Counſel, and as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to approve of that which the Counſel for the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ſhall urge againſt it, and for want of knowledge to guide them in their Judgements, to be incertain, and inſtable, making an order one day at the inſtigation of the Plaintiff, and another the next day quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to it at the requeſt of the Defendant, be like <hi>Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> blown with every wind of Doctrine, and like <hi>Bowls</hi> run only according to the <hi>Byas</hi> ſhall be put upon them; one will like the <hi>Mole</hi> in the Fable, think himſelf the moſt clear ſighted of all his fellows, another help to miſlead himſelf, and others by endeavouring to make men believe that which he ſpeaks is from <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> when he never <hi>ſpake</hi> with him, or knows how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound his written word; another will have a fancy of the <hi>Spirit</hi> or think himſelf guifted, when he himſelf would not truſt the moſt <hi>guifted</hi> Trades-man to ſettle a Daughters <hi>joynture,</hi> or make his Conveyance, &amp; when they ſhall have nothing of learning or Law to make uſe of but their own will &amp; weak apprehenſions, will make ſuch kind of Juſtice as will be had from them more <hi>arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> than that of a Tyrant, whoſe will and purpoſe of governing without <hi>Laws</hi> when he knows them, cannot
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61188:22"/> be ſo laſting and dangerous as the will of thoſe men of ignorance, which ſhall be only guided by the neceſſity of an <hi>invincible</hi> ignorance, and may prove to be a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter oppreſſion to the people, than it thoſe that ſhall be thus made to be corrupt, or to do like unrighteous Judges had been knowingly wicked, for that the one ſort doth commit numberleſſe <hi>errors</hi> by not knowing them, and the other committs but a <hi>few,</hi> becauſe they dare not adventure to do it often. Whereas the old conſtitutions and courſe of the Laws of <hi>England</hi> (as ill as the propoſers think of them) knew how to ſerve the people better, by making choice of ſuch men for Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as by Seven years ſtudy in an <hi>Innes</hi> of Court, or <hi>Colledge</hi> of Law had come to the degree of <hi>Barreſters,</hi> And from thence after a great number of years pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and continuance of Study to be <hi>Readers</hi> of the Law to the Innes of Court, whereof they were, after that <hi>Serjeants</hi> at Law, and after that for their eminency of parts and honeſty to be <hi>Judges,</hi> where by a continual Study, obſervation, and practice of the Law from their age of 16 or 17. until they came to be (as it moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly happens before they come to be Judges) above <hi>Threeſcore</hi> years of age, they became to be great Maſters of reaſon, and ſo fully experimented in the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the <hi>Law,</hi> and Cuſtoms of the <hi>Nation,</hi> as by their knowledge therein, and of the <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Cannon</hi> Laws which border upon them, and ſo many <hi>Caſes</hi> and experiments as had in all that time paſſed through the courſe of their Studies, and practice, as they were <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable in the gates of their people,</hi> and appeared compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able to contradict or rectifie Hundreds of other <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iers</hi> that moved or pleaded before them, and not only to adviſe the Supreme <hi>Authority,</hi> when they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61188:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> to it, concerning the making or executing of Laws, but to apply fit remedies to every mans action or grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance that came before them, and had all their life after no other <hi>Trade</hi> or profeſſion to divert or call off their <hi>thoughts</hi> from a continual Study of the Law, and right adminiſtration of juſtice.</p>
               <p>But if it ſhall be ſaid, that all that <hi>Catalogue</hi> of evills will be prevented by a carefull choice, or election of ſuch as ſhall be made Judges, out of the beſt, or moſt knowing of the people, that will but, little amend the matter, when the <hi>Lawiers,</hi> all but ſuch as ſhall be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to make one of the five in every County (who as to the Adminiſtration of Juſtice are the beſt and moſt knowing of the people) ſhall be laid aſide, and forbid to be choſen, for there muſt needs be a ſtrange electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when <hi>blind</hi> men ſhall be imployed to buy pictures, or the Boys in every pariſh to chooſe their School-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters. And if there could be any election without the guide or direction of a party or faction, it will not be uneaſie to gueſſe, whether the <hi>Self conceited,</hi> well <hi>known,</hi> little <hi>wiſdom</hi> of the <hi>multitude</hi> doth moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carry them, or to believe that the knowledge of the Law, in one of every 5 of thoſe Countie Judges, when 4 or the Major part of them ſhall be at liberty to be ignorant, will as little help the buſineſſe, as <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the <hi>Copper-Smith,</hi> and <hi>Demetrius</hi> the <hi>Silver Smith</hi> did <hi>Paul</hi> in the preaching of the Goſpel, or if it ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that one of every five of thoſe <hi>Judges</hi> of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Courts being a Lawyer (though it may by, they may be ſuch as have have only the name or Title of it, or for want of practice have loſt, or are to ſeek what they have read of it) ſhould be ſo much relyed upon for their judgements, as to be able to guide and govern
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61188:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> the reſt which are no Lawiers, To what end ſhould the Common-wealth be at the charge of ſuch <hi>Ciphers,</hi> or thoſe <hi>Ciphers</hi> ſhould only ſit to receive or take ſuch <hi>Figures,</hi> as the Suitors or people ſhall add unto them? The Lawier-<hi>Judges,</hi> if they chance to be as wiſe as <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſes,</hi> will be but ſet to plow with ſuch kind of <hi>Cattle</hi> as he did; and therefore it was not unwiſely ſaid to King <hi>Iames</hi> by the <hi>Conde de Gondomar</hi> that grand <hi>Spaniſh</hi> poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician, who when he had demanded of him, what was the reaſon he had put the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon,</hi> who was ſo eminent a wiſe man out of his place, and left in the <hi>Chancery</hi> Sir <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> who by his ignorance committed many more errors, and the King had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> adviſed &amp; importuned him to put him out, becauſe he was a <hi>knave</hi> (though in truth it was only ſome of his corrupt ſervants had abuſ'd him) replyed, that they had a <hi>Proverb</hi> or ſaying in <hi>Spain,</hi> that it was better to have a Thief in a <hi>Vinyard,</hi> than an <hi>Aſſe,</hi> for that the one took but what he ſtole without ſpoiling the <hi>Vinyard,</hi> but the other trod down and ſpoiled all before him.</p>
               <p>Which may come to be ſadly enough experimented in our own caſes, when the liberties and <hi>properties</hi> of the people ſhall be loſt, and made uncertain by thoſe that ſhould take a care of them; when thoſe that ſhall be as the Watchmen of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and neither ſlumber nor ſleep, ſhall have neither eyes to ſee, nor ears to hear, neither underſtand their Office, or know how to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute it, wherein it is not the well meaning of thoſe that ſhall undertake ſo weighty a buſineſſe, will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to protect them from the great ſin of preſumption, which they ſhall incur by taking a charge upon them they could not perform, nor <hi>ſecure</hi> the people from the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61188:24"/> damage and loſſes they ſhall ſuſtain by them, when time and authority ſhall beget in them a power, and that power like a Loadſtone, draw in and allure facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and parties, and thoſe factions and parties buſie themſelves in miſleading their good intentions, out of the narrow and ſeldom troden path of <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the great road of partiallity and oppreſſion.</p>
               <p>From whom if there ſhould be no appeals, or ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing further for Juſtice, it would not only be contrary to what was counſelled by <hi>Jethro,</hi> ordained by God himſelf, and practiſed by <hi>Moſes</hi> in bringing the moſt difficult cauſes, or thoſe that could not be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the ſmaller Courts, to the Judgement of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Courts, or the Supreme authority, but to all other Laws and governments of the world whatſoever, and make every one of thoſe new little Courts to be too much independent.</p>
               <p>Or if there ſhould be an allowance of appeals, make as many, if there ſhould be but a hundred in a year, from every one of thoſe new County Courts (which is like to be the leaſt at the loweſt computation) for if there were no real grievances, many will as they did, and do ſtill uſe to doe in the the Civil <hi>Law,</hi> Appeal to win time, or ſhelter themſelves from the extremity of an adverſary) as may amount to 5000 in every year, and every of thoſe appeals bring to the people ſo many ſecond <hi>hearings,</hi> and a double expence of time and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, from which alſo, if there ſhould be any Law made to obſtruct or hinder them, by ſome mulct or ſum of money, ordered to be paid or depoſited upon the brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of every appeal, ſo as few ſhall have the mind or <hi>ability</hi> to goe through with it, that will but raiſe the diſcontent and cry of the people higher, when they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61188:24"/> ſhall find themſelves ſent on an <hi>errand,</hi> to receive Law or Juſtice from thoſe that underſtand it not, and for want of underſtanding in their <hi>Judges,</hi> be caſt either into a greater controverſie, or an appeal to complain of a grievance, and when they think they ſhould have better Juſtice, muſt not have it, becauſe they cannot be at the price or <hi>hazard</hi> is put upon it: Or if the Judges ſhould be fined, as ſome would have it, for their errors (though by the Law as long agoe as King <hi>Edgar,</hi> a <note place="margin">In ll <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gari</hi> cap. 1 &amp; in Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liel. 1 cap. 15</note> Judge was not to be fined, if he would make oath, that he did as well as he could, or that he did it only by <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi> or miſtake, and not of <hi>Malice,</hi> or by corruption) they that have any wit or eſtate, will rather quit their places to ſuch as have neither of them, then take upon them, or continue ſuch a place of continual ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and unquiet, and then the matter will be fairly mended, and beſides, there will be no ſmall difficulty at any time to aſſign or faſten the errors upon the Judges, who it may be for want of skil were miſlead by the Plaintiffs or Defendants themſelves, or had not the matter or fact clearly ſtated before them, and then there will be no reaſon to lay the fault upon the Judges, when they did as well as they could, and they might have choſen wiſer.</p>
               <p>Such new County Courts will beget in every Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince ſeveral Laws and <hi>Jurisdictions</hi> or power (for as long as there ſhall be inequality of riches or places (which ever was and ever ought to be) there will be powers, and authorities over-awing one another) one power will grow greater than another, and perhaps too powerfull for the other parts of the Government, and commit all manner of injuſtice and oppreſſion.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the Nation, which next to the Military
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61188:25"/> and protection part of it, is and ought to be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt care of the Supreme power, and is ſo much the more Superior to the other, as it is the end of it, and not only helps to put the Sword again into the <hi>Scabbard,</hi> when it is drawn, but very much conduces to keep it from comming out again, and is in the ordinary exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution thereof at this time truſted out into leſſe than twelve hands in the ordinary Courts of Law at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> will by theſe propoſals upon very ſmall ſecurity be truſted and put into the hands of Two Hundred and Fifty men more, who will want that <hi>wiſdom</hi> as well as <hi>eſtates,</hi> which the other have to make them reſponſal; whereby the Supreme power of the Nation, may by its being too much divided and diffuſed into ſuch leſſer bodies, come to want that ſtrength and intireneſs it hath formerly had and enjoyed in the ſeveral ſucceſſion of Kings for almoſt One Thouſand years together, by kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their reſidence in the chief Citie or part of the Nation, As <hi>David</hi> and the Kings of <hi>Juda</hi> did at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and as all other Kings and Eſtates do in other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with their chief <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi> about them, where the <hi>pulſe,</hi> contents and <hi>diſcontents</hi> of the People, from all parts of the body <hi>Politicque</hi> may be felt, whither all their Complaints or principal buſineſſe might <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate</hi> and come, and paſſe to and fro, like the <hi>blood</hi> from all parts of the Body, to the <hi>Heart,</hi> and from thence back again to all parts of the Body, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Common ſenſe did from time to time bring in its Intelligence to the great <hi>Counſel</hi> which was holden in the <hi>Brayn</hi> for preſervation of the Heart as wel as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very part of the body.</p>
               <p>They that heretofore could with one expence and charges proſecute a ſuit at Law at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and at
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61188:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſame time attend the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or their <hi>Committees,</hi> the Council of State, the <hi>Exchequer</hi> or Committee of revenue, and the motions and deſigns of their adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, who it may be had bills in <hi>Chancery,</hi> or actions in ſome other Court of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> depending againſt them at the ſame time, and do many other buſineſſes whilſt they remained there, meet and confer with Friends, or Foreiners, or people of all parts of the Nation, could make bargains, and diſpoſe of Children, and have the help or aſſiſtance in their Suits at Law of the ableſt &amp; moſt eminent Lawiers in their ſeveral Innes of <hi>Court</hi> or <hi>Stations,</hi> muſt now perhaps goe to the Shire Town as a Plaintiff or Defendant at Law, and to <hi>London</hi> for his other buſineſſe, &amp; be content with ſuch Lawiers only in his own Country as are there reſident, when it may be there are none eminent, or very able, to be had there, or be inforced to procure ſuch as are to come at great rates, one hundred or Two hundred miles at a time, from the places where they inhabit, and that Country and many a more diſtreſſed Client want them in the mean time.</p>
               <p>Such a multitude of Courts will throw many men, eſpecially ſuch as have great dealing and multitude of buſineſſe with men of many Counties, into ſo many journeys and perplexities, as they ſhall never be at leiſure from attending one Court or other, whereas now one man that hath occaſion to proſecute Actions of debt againſt one <hi>Hundred</hi> Debtors living in 20 Counties, diſperſed over the whole Nation, doth his buſineſſe without Travelling or ſending any further than to <hi>London,</hi> Streightens and gives men no time to provide their evidence or Witneſſes, and puts the Lawiers as well as their Clients by ſo much atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61188:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> at ſo many ſeveral Courts into a continual atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance or Travelling from one Shire to another, and will not a little diſtract mens affairs, to have an Action at one and the ſame time to be tryed or called upon at <hi>London, Cornwall, Barwick,</hi> and <hi>Pembroke</hi> Shire, where they ſhould be perſonally at every one of them, and can be but at one, and muſt be in a continual unquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and trouble, when all the year ſhall be as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Term, or time of controverſie, and when they ſhall be enforced to neglect their affairs of Husbandry and Harveſt, to travel and tire themſelves through all the lines of the <hi>Circumference,</hi> when they might have a ſhorter way to and from the <hi>Centre,</hi> which by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion of Terms and Vacations, and the known and convenient times of <hi>Aſsizes,</hi> when the Terms were ended, was by the Laws now in being ſufficiently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented.</p>
               <p>But theſe are not like to be all the inconveniences neither, for if the Courts of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> ſhall beſides the Two and Fifty County Courts to be taken out of them be cut into leſſer pieces, by giving cogniſance of pleas, of Actions, of Treſpaſſe, Battery, and the like, and of Actions of debt under 40 ſhillings as ſome would have it, there will then be as many ſmaller Courts as will make us up above 2600 Courts, the Judges whereof will look to be paid as well as the Judges of the other Courts for the neglect of their own buſineſſe, to take care of other mens, and if they ſhould have but 50 l. <hi>per annum</hi> a peece for ſtanding ſalaries, will make a yearly charge to the State, of above Sixty Five Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> or if they ſhall be prohibited their taking of Fees, will grow careleſſe and nnwilling to be troubled, pretend to be ſick or abſent when they
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61188:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> are not, or half hear cauſes, or like ſome of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex,</hi> or Suburbian Juſtices take a great deal more in Fees and <hi>Incomes</hi> than that would come to, and doe as little for it as they uſe to doe in matters of Breach of this Peace or petty Brawls, which is to bind them over to the <hi>Seſsions,</hi> and take their Fees for it, and for thoſe cauſes which they ſhall adventure to determine beget in a year more appeals than there ſhall be Juſtices of the peace, which in a year but after the rate of 2600 petty Courts or more, but 40 Times appealed from, every one of them, will yeeld to the people above One Hundred Thouſand appeals, which may coſt them no ſmall mony &amp; time to maintain, and bring to a hearing, and by ſuch double and treble agitations, diſcovery of Titles, and evidence, and half hearing of their cauſes, make their contentions grow as endleſſe as their Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:61188:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> That it will not only raiſe up again thoſe old grievances, which were formerly the cauſe of diſuſing, or reſtraining the Sheriffs <hi>Turns, County Courts,</hi> Court <hi>Barons,</hi> and Hundred Courts, and ſuch like petty Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions, but far exceed them.</head>
               <p>BUt ſurely they that thus erre for want of knowledge, and do too much build upon their own <hi>ignorance,</hi> would, if they knew the reaſons that accompany our Laws, not be ſo forward to goe back again into thoſe evils which our Aunceſtors and the care of former <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments</hi> did bring us out of, nor take that to be a new and better way, is but a going back again into them, and a reviving of old grievances.</p>
               <p>We ſhall therefore ſhew them, what they were, &amp; let them ſee they are very like unto that they are now: ſo willing to eſtabliſh amongſt us. The Courts called Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, <hi>Wapentakes,</hi> &amp; the County <hi>Courts,</hi> had their original by conſent of moſt Authors from K. <hi>Alfred,</hi> who <note n="n" place="margin">Polidor in Guliel. Conq. Spelman Gloſs. in verb. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitia</note> would not truſt them with Capital or Chief matters Criminal, but reſerved them <hi>ad Majores Juſtitiarios.</hi> And though he gave them power to determine leſſer matters, yet did he as well as King <hi>Ina</hi> his predeceſſor, and thoſe <hi>Saxon</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> Kings, <hi>Edward</hi> the elder, <hi>Athelſtane, Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert, Edgar, Canutus,</hi> and <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſor which ſucceeded him, give leave to any to appeal, <hi>pro defectu Iuſtitiae,</hi> or when right could not be obtained.</p>
               <p>But that being in a time when the ſmallneſſe of Commerce, paucity, poverty, and inculture of people, little acquaintance with Navigation, or Forein Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, continual wars one with another, in a <hi>Heptar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:61188:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> or multiplicity of Kings, and Invaſions of the <hi>Danes,</hi> could not allow them much buſineſſe at Law, and if they had where withall to have been contentious, were ſo bound up by certain ſtrict Laws, fit only for a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were newly eſcaped out of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> and lived in a Country more like a deſart or <hi>Wildernes,</hi> than as now it is, as they could not if they would have many Suites at Law to trouble the leſſer or greater <hi>Courts</hi> withall, for in every Tithing <note n="o" place="margin">In ll. E. Confeſs. cap. 20.</note> or <hi>Friborgh,</hi> every man anſwer'd ſo for one another, as they were bound to bring offenders to Juſtice, every <note n="p" place="margin">In ll. Edga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri c. 6 &amp; in legibus Ethelredi cap. 1.</note> man did put in ſecurities to do right to one another, the Lord for <note n="q" place="margin">In ll. H. 1. c. 23 et 41. in ll. Canu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti c. 25 &amp; 28. &amp; in ll. Ethelſt. cap. 10.</note> his Tenants, and the Maſter fot his Servants; <note n="r" place="margin">In legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Edw. Reg. cap. 1.</note> no man bought any thing without a pledge or voucher, or exchanged goods but before a Magiſtrate, or the Miniſter, or Lord of the Mannor, he that <note n="s" place="margin">In ll. Alu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redi c. 33. &amp; in ll. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelſtani cap. 8.</note> received a Stranger, anſwered for any thing <note n="t" place="margin">In ll. E. Reg &amp; in ll. Canuti cap. 64.</note> he had done in the place from whence he came; no man under a penalty harboured a <hi>Fugitive,</hi> or kept him from Juſtice, he that was miſdoubted <note n="u" place="margin">In ll. Inae. In ll. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gari c. 2 &amp; l. Canuti li. 16.</note> or accuſed, was in many things to purge himſelf, by his own oath, or of ſo many of his neighbours, &amp; if any had (<hi>w</hi>) complained before they had demanded right in thoſe leſſer Courts, were fined and puniſhed.</p>
               <p>Yet though thoſe Courts had their work ſo much done to their hands, the people were ſo little notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſatisfied with their Juſtice, as we ſhall find <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Conquerour</hi> afterwards to have his Chief <hi>Iuſtice</hi> to at tend him for the determining of ſuch cauſes as came to demand his Juſtice, his Son <hi>William Ruſus</hi> the like, and by that time the Crown came to <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, who was not alſo without his Chief Juſtice, the Laws began to take notice of the different Laws of Provinces, of a <hi>penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Iudicum</hi> in <note n="w" place="margin">In ll. H. 1. c. 7.</note> ſome Hundreds, &amp; of violences &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:61188:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> which made [a neceſſity of carrying ſome cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes upon denying right to be done in thoſe Courts to the County Courts, (all actions of breach of the peace, and pleas of Treaſons, Murder, Coynings of monies, and many more which are enumerated in his Law <hi>de Jure Regis,</hi> then belonging to the King.)</p>
               <p>King <hi>Stephen</hi> had his Chief Juſtices, and when King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond comes to raign, the <hi>Kingdom</hi> was ſo full of exactions and oppreſſions, as he is much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled how to find a man fit, and honeſt enough to make <note place="margin">Chronic. Jo Brom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</note> a Chief Juſtice of, though he had tryed Abbots and <hi>Earls, Commanders</hi> and Souldiers, and Spiritual men as well as Secular, and therfore we find him upon the peoples Complaints of their want of juſtice from ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts of the Kingdom in a Parliament at <hi>Nottingham in Anno Domini</hi> One Thouſand One Hundred Seventy Six, (in imitation of what had been formerly done in <hi>France,</hi> 
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Spelman Gloſſar in verb. Juſtic. tinerant.</note> by <hi>Carolus Calvus in Anno Eight Hundred Fifty</hi> and <hi>Three</hi>) ordaining Iuſtices <hi>Itinerant</hi> or in <hi>Eyre</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their allotments of ſeveral <hi>Shires,</hi> but all Fines levied in the Kings Court, Actions of debt, writs of Aſſize, Dower, advowſon, and all or moſt pleas of conſequence brought and held in the Kings Courts (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſuch as were ſometimes allowed by his <hi>Writs</hi> or <note place="margin">lib. 11. c. 1.</note> Commiſſion to be determined in the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> Court or the Hundred, or Courts Barons) for any might then <note place="margin">lib. 12. c. 7.</note> remove an Action from the leſſer Courts to the <hi>Kings,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">3 c. 3. et 5.</note> or have an <hi>Accedas ad Curiam,</hi> or prohibition, if we may believe <hi>Glanvil,</hi> 
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Glanvil lib. 10. c. 1.</note> who was his Chief Juſtice.</p>
               <p>In his Son <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt his time the power and privileges of <hi>Sheriffs</hi> did grow ſo great in their Counties and Courts, as ſome <hi>Biſhops</hi> whoſe places in thoſe times led them quite off from <hi>Secular</hi> imployments, were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61188:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> to take upon them the Offices of <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> but were queſtioned for it afterwards, and forbid by the <hi>Pope</hi> to intermedle any more in them. But about 9 <hi>H</hi> 3. the Complaints of the people did ſo follow the King and his Chief Juſtice, as it was enacted by Parliament that <hi>Common pleas ſhould not follow the Court, but be holden in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">9 H. 3. c.</note> 
                  <hi>ſome place certain,</hi> in 52 H. 3. Complaints were made <note place="margin">52 H. 3. cap. 11.</note> in <hi>Parliament, that great men, and diverſe others, refuſed to be juſtified by the King and his Court, as they ought and were wont to be, in the time of his progenitors, but took grear reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and diſtreſses of their Neighbours, and others, until they had amends and Fines at their own pleaſure; And would not ſuffer delivery of ſuch diſtreſſes as they had taken of their own authority, diſtrained men to do Suit to their Courts, that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eodem Anno c. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>were not bound by their Deeds or Enfeoffments, amerced men wrongfully for default of Common Summons, and compelled</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>c.</hi> 17 &amp; 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Freeholders to anſwer for their Freeholds without the Kings writ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the reign of his Son <hi>E.</hi> 1. as appeareth by <hi>Britton</hi> who compiled a book of the Laws by the Kings ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, all men by a Publick <hi>Cry</hi> and proclamation were to come with their plaints, cauſes, and actions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Juſtices in <hi>Eyre,</hi> when they came into the <hi>Counties,</hi> and all other pleas to <hi>Ceaſe,</hi> and all thoſe who claimed any <hi>Franchyſes</hi> were to ſhew their Title to them, and ſpecial enquiries made of <hi>Sheriffs, Bayliffs,</hi> and <hi>Stewards,</hi> concerning the execution of their <hi>Offices,</hi> maintaining <hi>Quarrels,</hi> amercing men wrongfully, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting <hi>extortions,</hi> and holding pleas in debt or treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe above <hi>Forty Shillings,</hi> which did not belong to <note place="margin">Britton c. 2. 20. 21.</note> them, 3 <hi>E. 1. cap. 15. Sheriffs and others did let out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſuch as were not repleviſeable, and kept in priſon ſuch as were</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:61188:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beaſts were diſtrayned and carried into another County; Great men and their</hi> Bayliffs <hi>did attach and arreſt others, paſsing through their Juriſdiction, and compelled them to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer upon Contracts covenants and Treſpaſſes</hi> done out of their power <hi>and Juriſdiction,</hi> 13 E. 1. cap. 13. <hi>Sheriffs did in their Turnes feign men to be indicted before them for fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, and Treſpaſſes, and impriſoned them, and exacted mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of them, when they were not lawfully indicted by Twelve Jurors, Lords of Courts, and others that kept Courts and</hi> Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, <note place="margin">cap. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>intending to grieve their</hi> Inferiors, <hi>did procure others to enter Actions in their Courts, and to move matters againſt them, and to put in ſureties and pledges, or to purchaſe writs, and compel men to follow their</hi> Countie <hi>Courts, Hundreds, Wapentakes, or other like Courts, until they had made Fine at their will, Sheriffs, Hundredors, and Bayliffs of liberties, did uſe to grieve ſuch as were in ſubjection to them, putting in Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes and Juries men diſeaſed and decrepit, and ſuch as dwelt in other Counties, to extort money from them, and Bayliffs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to grieve their Inferiors to the end they might exact money of them, did ſend Strangers to take diſtreſſes, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that the parties ſo diſtrained, and not knowing ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, would not ſuffer the diſtreſſes to be taken;</hi> 33 Ed. 1. <hi>Stewards and Bayliffs of great Lords did undertake to bear, or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain quarrels which concerned other parties.</hi> 38 E. 3. <hi>Great</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">cap. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>men came armed and with power to diſturb the execution of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> 4 E. 3. cap. 11. <hi>Diverſe as well great men as other made Alliances, confederacies, and conſpiracies, to maintain parties, pleas, and quarrels, whereby divers were wrongfully diſ-inherited, ranſomed, and deſtroyed.</hi> 14 Ed. 3. cap. 16. <hi>Enqueſts and Juries were taken in diverſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties where no Juſtice did come, to the great miſchief of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that did ſue, as alſo of the good people that were impannel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and Sheriffs did let their Hundred Courts at great rates,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61188:29"/> to the impoveriſhing and oppreſsion of the People.</hi> 17 E. 3. <hi>The</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> in 38.</note> 
                  <hi>Commons Petition that exceſsive Fines impoſed on them by ſuch as have Leets might be redreſſed,</hi> 20 Ed. 3. cap. 6. <hi>Bayliffs of Franchiſes, and their under-miniſters did commit mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and imbracery of Jurors, and took gifts, rewards, and other profits, which they did take to array pannels, and to execute them, to the ſubverſion of the Laws, and diſturbance of Common right.</hi> 31. Ed. 3. cap. 15. <hi>Sheriffs held their Turnes in time of Harveſt, and hindred the people.</hi> 20 Rich. 2. cap. 10. <hi>Notorious Theeves were delivered by favourable inqueſts procured to the great hinderance of the people; Lords,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">cap. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>and other great men did uſe to ſit upon the Bench with Iuſtices of Aſsize.</hi> 17. Ed. 4. cap. 2. <hi>Courts of Pypowder were miſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Stewards, Vnder-Stewards, and Baylifls holding pleas for contracts made out of the Fairs.</hi> 1 Rich. 3. cap. 4. <hi>Diverſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences and perjuries did dayly happen in diverſe Shires of</hi> England, <hi>by untrue verdicts before Sheriffs in their Turns, by perſons of no behaviour, nor dreading God, nor the worlds ſhame.</hi> cap. 6. <hi>Courts of Pypowder were miſuſed by Stewards and Bayliffs upon feigned plaints to trouble men to whom they owe evil will to make men loſe their Fair, or to get favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inqueſts, whereby many coming to the Fairs were grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly vexed for contracts made out of the Fair, The Lords loſt their profits of their Fairs, and the People wanted thoſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes, would otherwiſe come to them.</hi> II. Hen. 7. cap. 15. <hi>Great extortion was uſed in divers Countries, by Vnder-Sheriffs, Shire-Clerks, and other Officers, holding and keeping County-Courts, and in the name of the Sheriffs, by entring Plaints without the Plaintiffs direction againſt Defendants, to the intent that if they appear not, they may be amerced; or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred Plaints in the name of ſuch as were dead, and to that end did not at all attach or ſummon the Defendants, but cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſaid amerciaments to be levied.</hi> 3 H. 8. cap. 12.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61188:30"/> 
                  <hi>Great extortions and oppreſsions were by Sheriffs, and their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, by impanelling ſuch as will be perjured.</hi> 26 Henry 8. cap. 4. <hi>Juries in</hi> Wales <hi>gave untrue verdicts, becauſe upon indictments of Murder, and Felons, the Kindred and Friends to ſuch offenders had acceſſe to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>27 H. 8. cap. 7. <hi>Divers oppreſsions, maintenance, imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries, riots, treſpaſſes, &amp;c. were in</hi> Cheſter <hi>and</hi> Wales, <hi>by reaſon that common juſtice was not administered there as in other places, by reaſon of a diverſe miniſtration of Juſtice. Diverſe authorities of juſtice appertaining to the King had</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">cap. 24.</note> 
                  <hi>been granted away, to the great hindrance and delay of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">cap. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>By reaſon of diverſity of Laws and uſages in</hi> Wales <hi>and</hi> England, <hi>great diſcords, variance and ſedition have ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen betwixt the People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which irregularities of Small <hi>Courts,</hi> ſo all along from time to time complained of in Parliament, were not only the cauſe of making thoſe many Acts of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament in thoſe ſeveral years to redreſſe thoſe <hi>grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> but of the making of ſeveral other Acts of <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> As that in 13 <hi>E. 1. cap.</hi> 30. authoriſing Juſtices of <hi>Niſi prius,</hi> to go at certain times of the year into the <hi>Counties;</hi> that of 27 <hi>E. 1. cap.</hi> 3. and 4. to make thoſe <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Aſſize <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of Gaol delivery, and that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts and recogniſances taken before <hi>Iustices</hi> of either <hi>Bench</hi> ſhould be taken in time of vacation before any of the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> before whom the <hi>plea</hi> is brought. That of 28 <hi>E. 1. cap.</hi> 10. that againſt <hi>Conſpirators,</hi> falſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, procurers of enqueſts, and <hi>Iuries,</hi> remedie ſhould be had, by a writ out of the <hi>Chancery,</hi> and that the Juſtices of both Benches and Juſtices aſſigned to take <hi>Aſsizes,</hi> ſhould, when they come into the Country, upon every plaint made unto them, award enqueſts. Char of 12 <hi>E. 2. cap.</hi> 3. and 4. that enqueſts and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61188:30"/> in pleas of <hi>Land</hi> that require great examination, ſhould be taken in the Country before two Juſtices of the Bench, and that which they ſhall have done ſhall be reported in the <hi>Bench</hi> at a certain day there to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled, and thereupon Judgement ſhall be given; And to provide that inqueſts and Juries ſhould notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding be taken in the Bench if they came. That of 2 <hi>E. 3. cap.</hi> 2. that Aſſizes, <hi>Attaints,</hi> and Certifications be taken before the <hi>Juſtices</hi> commonly aſſigned, which be good men and lawfull, <hi>having knowledge of the Law,</hi> and none other. That of 14 <hi>E. 3. cap.</hi> 16. that <hi>niſi pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſhall be granted, as well at the Suit of the Defendant as of the <hi>Plaintiff,</hi> and before a Juſtice of another Court, then where the Suit dependeth, and if it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that none of the Juſtices of the one Bench or the other may go into the Country, then <hi>Niſi prius</hi> to be granted before the <hi>Chief Baron</hi> of the Exchequer if he <hi>be a man learned in the Law,</hi> and in caſe he cannot go, then before <hi>Juſtices</hi> aſſigned to take aſſizes in thoſe parts; ſo as one of the ſaid Juſtices aſſigned be Juſtice of the one <hi>Bench</hi> or the other, or the Kings <hi>Serjeants</hi> ſworn. That of 20 <hi>R. 2. cap.</hi> 10. that two learned men in the Law Juſtices of the peace ſhall be in Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Goal delivery. And of making the ſeveral Acts of Parliament, 28 <hi>E. 1. cap. 14. 9 E. 2. cap. 4. 4 E. 3. cap. 5. 9. E. 3. cap. 3. 14 E. 3. cap. 7. 28 E. 3. cap. 7. 1 R. 2. cap. 11. &amp; 1 H. 4. cap.</hi> 4. That none ſhould be Sheriffs and Bayliffs for above a year toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or but ſuch as had ſufficient to anſwer the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints</hi> of the people; that Bayliwicks, and <hi>Hundreds</hi> ſhould not be let to Farm at over great Rents; that Sheriffs <hi>Clerks</hi> ſhould not practiſe as Attorneys during their office; the Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> in 28 <hi>E. 1. cap.</hi> 4.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61188:31"/> That the <hi>Chancellor,</hi> and the <hi>Juſtices</hi> of the Kings <hi>Bench,</hi> ſhould follow the King, that he might have at all times near unto him ſome that were <hi>Learned</hi> in the Laws, which might be able daily to order ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as ſhould come unto the <hi>Court</hi> at all Times when need ſhould require; that of 28 <hi>E. 1. cap.</hi> 7. That the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable of <hi>Dover</hi> ſhould hold no pleas within the Caſtle gate, but ſuch as did belong to the keeping of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle; that of 30 <hi>E.</hi> the <hi>firſt,</hi> to queſtion by <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> all liberties to which there could not be a good Title ſhewn, for that to the <hi>King</hi> belonged the care of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> And that of 9 <hi>E. 3. cap.</hi> 5. at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the <hi>Commons,</hi> that Juſtices of Aſſize, <hi>Goal</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, <hi>Oyer</hi> and Terminer, ſhould every year at <hi>Michaelmas</hi> ſend their records to the <hi>Exchequer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And did put the Kings of this <hi>Nation</hi> into ſuch a continual watchfullneſſe and care of the due admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Juſtice to be done in the Counties and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote parts of this Nation, as the Juſtices of <hi>Aſsize</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver went their <hi>Circuits,</hi> but they either attended the King or his <hi>Chancellor</hi> to know what ſpecial mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were to be given in charge to the people, and did at their retorn upon any extraordinary thing that happened in their <hi>Circuits,</hi> give him, and his Council an account thereof; and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this their care, and the ſending of Juſtices twice a year into every County, which did much awe, and keep in order thoſe <hi>County</hi> Courts, Sheriffs <hi>Turnes,</hi> and the <hi>Actions</hi> of Stewards in their Court Leets, and Court Barons, and that the wiſdom of former times took all the care they could to have the hundred <hi>Courts,</hi> Courts Leet, and Courts <hi>Baron,</hi> Countie <hi>Courts,</hi> and Sheriffs <hi>Turnes,</hi> to be executed by able and honeſt men,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:61188:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> as we may ſee in the reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, who would not allow, <hi>viles &amp; inopes perſonas,</hi> to be <hi>Legum Judices,</hi> or <hi>Stultos aut Improbos, ſed optimates qui non per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonam ſed opera dijudicent.</hi> And that <hi>Bayliffs</hi> were long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">in ll H. r. c. 9. &amp; 29.</note> Characterd by <hi>Fleta</hi> to be <hi>moribus &amp; legibus pro officio ſufficientes,</hi> and the Stewards <hi>in legibus conſuetudinibuſque</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Fleta lib. 20. 60 &amp; 65.</note> 
                  <hi>Provinciae, &amp; officio Seneſchalciae cognoſcentes;</hi> and that thoſe <hi>Franchiſes</hi> and little Courts were forfeitable by a <hi>miſuſer</hi> of them, all the care could be poſſiby taken to prevent it, nor the puniſhment or forfeiture which hung over them, could not ſo reſtrain or keep them in order, but that there were daily complaints made of them, and writs obtained from the Kings Courts to remedy them, as writs of <hi>right patent, Ne injuſte vexes ſuperſedeas,</hi> writs of <hi>right,</hi> writs of <hi>Pone, prohibitions,</hi> writs of falſe judgement, de <hi>executione judicii, Recordares, accedas ad Curiam, Cerciorares &amp; habeas Corpora,</hi> to remove cauſes, <note place="margin">Regiſter of writs.</note> writs to take one in <hi>Witherman,</hi> that would not ſuffer a man to be replevied, and writts of <hi>Error</hi> to County Courts. Inſomuch as the people were in the ſenſe of their own <hi>grievances</hi> which were never like to fail them in thoſe <hi>inferior</hi> Courts, and thoſe natural <hi>inclinations,</hi> and propenſities, which are in all Mankind to the <hi>beſt</hi> things, and that which may <hi>ſooneſt</hi> accompliſh their <hi>ends,</hi> ſo brought (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when they found that the Stewards or <hi>Judges</hi> of thoſe inferior Courts could not hold any <hi>proportion,</hi> or ſtand in the <hi>ballance</hi> with the Judges at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>) by degrees to a contempt and waving of the Countie <hi>Courts,</hi> Court <hi>Barons,</hi> and <hi>Hundred</hi> Courts, as they became to be generally <hi>diſuſed,</hi> or laid aſide (the people ſeldome appearing at them, when they were ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the Stewards as ſeldom keeping of them.)</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:61188:32"/>
               <p>For though it muſt be <hi>confeſſed</hi> that it may be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thatſome few men may by ſuch new <hi>Countie</hi> Courts ſave ſome labour, charges, or trouble, for once, or a a little while, as their particular caſes or conveniences, neighbourhood, or conditions of adverſaries may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be (for no doubt but there were ſome that did find good by the Courts of <hi>Star</hi>-Chamber, and High Commiſſion, and the Courts of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Marſhal ſea,</hi> and of the Marches of <hi>Wales</hi> and the <hi>North</hi> in every year of their many years or ages continuance, though they were afterwards taken away as grievances, yet thoſe particular <hi>benefits</hi> which ſome few of the People ſhall receive by theſe new to be erected Courts, will or can as little <hi>aſſure</hi> them, or their own poſterity from mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at ſome other time with thoſe many inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, may happen unto them afterwards, as it will do <hi>Thouſands</hi> more than themſelves, and the whole body of the people, that ſhall be prejudiced by it in the <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,</hi> for all that are or may be benefits to ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular men or places, have neither a poſſibility or <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity</hi> of being ſo in the general, and to all people of the Nation, or to thoſe very <hi>individuals</hi> at all times, or upon all occaſions, and therefore the making of a Law to forbid all <hi>uſury,</hi> or taking profit for mony lent, would not be profitable to the people in general, nor to thoſe men that at once might perhaps ſave ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in the payment of their debts, when they ſhall be more troubled after upon their next occaſions or want to borrow <hi>mony</hi> than that amounted unto, nor would it be for a publick or general good, that every <hi>Town</hi> or <hi>Village</hi> in the Nation ſhould have a <hi>Market</hi> kept every week it, though it might be good for ſome ſolitary Towns, in a <hi>Forreſt</hi> or upon the <hi>Woalds</hi> to have it ſo,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:61188:32"/> nor would the Country people that can be ſometimes content to ſupply their preſent or leſſer occaſions by the Pedlars at their own doors, be well pleaſed that they ſhould therefore be reſtrained from ſeeking better up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their greater disbuſements or occaſions, at the well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furniſhed <hi>Shops</hi> in the <hi>Cities,</hi> or that they ſhould have a <hi>Monopoly</hi> of only ſelling to them the worſer ſort of <hi>commodities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore, let any men of Learning, reaſon, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiality judge, if all this would not do when the little Courts could not proceed in any Action above Forty Shillings, but that the people were ſo frequently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced for want of Juſtice to remove their cauſes to the higher Courts, how many, very many Complaints and <hi>grievances</hi> there would have been if this way had been ſtopped or taken from them as is now deſired.</p>
               <p>Or whether the people of <hi>England,</hi> did any wrong to themſelves, in paſſing by thoſe little Courts where the <hi>Steward</hi> was moſt commonly ignorant, and the Suitors which were the Judges a great deal more, and were ſure enough to meet with ignorance, injuſtice, or oppreſſion, and if the cauſe were like to go well with them, to have it removed, upon any pretences of their adverſaries, to come to the Superiour Courts, where they ſhould be out of the danger of <hi>Appeals,</hi> and could not want Juſtice when they ſought it, nor protection in the ſeeking of it.</p>
               <p>Or whether they did not better to ſeek for Juſtice at the Well-head and Fountain of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> where they could not doubt of the skil and honeſty of their Judges, and the aſſiſtance of able Lawiers to plead for them, or to have their Actions tryed before ſome of the ſame Judges in their own Counties at the <hi>Aſsizes,</hi> and might
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61188:33"/> be diſpatched ſooner, and with leſſe trouble and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to both parties, than they could at a <hi>Second</hi> or <hi>Third</hi> hand, by removing their Actions from the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Court to the Countie Court, and from thence to <hi>Westminſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Common uſe or allowance of which more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and convenient way, if the reaſon of it had lain hid or concealed, had been enough to tell us and all after ages, the benefit and good which the people had by it, as well as that, of making <hi>bread</hi> with <hi>Wheat</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>acorns,</hi> or wearing <hi>cloaths</hi> inſtead of going <hi>naked,</hi> when the ignorance of our older fore-fathers allowed them no better, or the peoples leaving ſome <hi>Market</hi> Town to talk only of their <hi>Charter,</hi> whilſt their own convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces carries them to a better.</p>
               <p>For that muſt needs be out of all <hi>danger</hi> of <hi>error</hi> or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience which hath had ſo long an experimented &amp; conſtant allowance, when there was not heretofore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Petition</hi> in Parliament or to any the former Supreme Authorities againſt it, and when a general uſe or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience, not for one but for many ages ſucceſſively, hath brought it into a cuſtom, and univerſal <hi>approbation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſhould be now of a greater <hi>price,</hi> then to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed for all thoſe and more <hi>grievances,</hi> which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore filled our former <hi>Parliaments</hi> with Complaints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Countie</hi> Courts, Sheriffs Turnes, and <hi>Hundred</hi> Courts (for the Cryes of the poor and <hi>indigent,</hi> and their many <hi>ſmotherd</hi> oppreſſions could not always reach thither) will not only be <hi>raiſed</hi> up again and <hi>reſtored</hi> to the people with intereſt by theſe new eſtabliſhments, but far exceed them, and be like ſo many Councels of the Marches in every Countie.</p>
               <p>But they that have ingaged their Fancies to put ſo
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61188:33"/> great a diſturbance upon the people &amp; might in a <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> of it go quietly back again into their own <hi>Trades,</hi> do no tthink all this enough, unleſſe ſome augmentation be laid to the peoples grievances, by annexing of a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or Juriſdiction of <hi>equity,</hi> to every, or many of theſe little Courts, which may bring up a <hi>Brigade</hi> of Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences as a reſerve to the former.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> That the annexing of a Jurisdiction or power of equity, to every or many of thoſe new little Courts, will much increaſe the Peoples grievances, and turn that little Lawwhich ſhall be left into a courſe of arhitrarineſs</head>
               <p>FOr the annexing of the equitable part of the jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Chancery</hi> to the Courts or courſes of <hi>Common</hi> Law, when they ſhall be again eſtabliſhed, as ſome would have it in their propoſals or regulation of the Law, will, by giving every judge at Law a power of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, make a cauſe that would be begun and brought to hearing, and an end, in two <hi>Terms,</hi> continue Six or <hi>Seaven,</hi> and by a long and tedious courſe of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and croſſe examining of Witneſſes, be ten times more chargeable to the people, and when there is not now one in every <hi>hundred</hi> cauſes at Law, that go af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Chancery, and might be fewer if there were more <hi>Conſcience</hi> in men, and the Rules of the Court better obſerved, make every ſingle cauſe a double one, and a Suit in <hi>Chancery</hi> as well as at Common-Law when it needs not, put the Judges at Law (who before were ſo tyed up to their Oaths, and a preſcript Rule of Law, as to weep over their own Sons and neareſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, rather than to deviate, or Swerve from the Text
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61188:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> or Rule of Law, into too great a liberty of expoſition or arbitrarineſſe: Or if the equity of every cauſe ſhould be put to the Jurors, give us <hi>Twelve</hi> men of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity or <hi>Chancellors</hi> in every cauſe, will hardly be brought to underſtand it, but be ſo puzled in the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of it, as it will hardly, or, if at all, very tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly be drawn from them, if the matter of equity ſhall be left to the Judges alone, there will be little need of the Jury, if the Jury alone, as little of the Judge, ſuch an intermingling or uniting of the power of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the power of Law, can produce no better ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect then to make every one to begin or make his Suit or action, would otherwiſe have been ended in a ſhort courſe of Law, in a long examination of circumſtances of equity or way of <hi>Chancery,</hi> and render the equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or arbitrary part of thoſe Courts ſo <hi>Superior,</hi> and predominant to the legal, as in a ſhort time it will <hi>alter</hi> or take away the force and power of it: For the Judge will have a double power and Capacity to take which <hi>Hand</hi> he will, and to judge according to this or that Circumſtance, which he ſhall like beſt; the Law will be then faſt and looſe at pleaſure, and will not be as it is now <hi>Lex a Ligando,</hi> nor <hi>Lex a Legendo,</hi> but ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain and inconſtant, as to alter or diſſolve it ſelf into an equity of this or that circumſtance, which can lay the faſteſt hold upon it, or the Iudge, and be ſo much at the expoſition or command of the Iudges, who were wont to be commanded by the Laws, as every thing they would have muſt be turned into an <hi>equity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which the wiſdom of our Parliaments and Laws were ſo far from ſuffering, as they would not ſuffer the <hi>Chancery</hi> to meddle with matters of Law, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:61188:34"/> in former ages ſo <hi>jealous</hi> of it, as they petitioned in former Parliaments, that judgements ſhould not be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in cauſes of Law, but by proceſs at Law, and that they might not appear in <hi>Chancery</hi> upon <hi>Sub poenas,</hi> or writs of <hi>quibuſdam certis de cauſis,</hi> when there was reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy at Law, and was the cauſe that the <hi>Chancery</hi> hath heretofore and to this time kept themſelves to their conſtant courſe of allowing <hi>Demurrers,</hi> and diſcharging ſuch cauſes as might be relieved at Law. For if it were formerly a grievance for the <hi>Chancery</hi> to determine mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at Law, The putting or mingling of matters of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity into Courts of <hi>Law,</hi> will be but one and the ſame thing, and as like to be a <hi>grievance</hi> as the other.</p>
               <p>Of which the late Parliament, in their argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Councel</hi> of the <hi>Marches</hi> of the North in 1641, were ſo ſenſible, as they alleaged it would be prejudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to the people if the <hi>King</hi> ſhould be permitted to <hi>canton</hi> out a part of his Kingdom to be tryed by <note n="z" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hides</hi> argument in <hi>April,</hi> 1641 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lords in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by order of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</note> Commiſſion (though it were according to the Rules of Law) or to erect new Courts of <hi>Chancery,</hi> and that the latitude and power of the Iudges of that Court of the <hi>Marches,</hi> in judging according to equity and diſcretion, was the <hi>Quick-ſand</hi> that ſwallowed up the peoples property and liberty, and that the very <hi>adminiſtration</hi> of Iuſtice founded upon ſuch illegal principles, was a grievance, and oppreſſion to the people; and the Houſe of Commons in the late Parliament (of which ſome of the now Members were then a part) were ſo far from altering their opinion in that particular, as in their grand remonſtrance of the State of the Kingdom, the <note n="a" place="margin">Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance 15 <hi>December 1641</hi>
                  </note> 15 of <hi>December,</hi> 1641 repeating what good they had done for the people, and what Courts they had taken away, they reckon that, and ſome other arbitrary
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:61188:35"/> Courts, and called them the forges of miſery, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</p>
               <p>And yet this is not all the propoſers would have, nor will their appetite of change be ſatisfied, or the confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be compleated, unleſſe the Lawiers may be totally extirped, &amp; the Innes of Court and Chancery, which u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to breed them, be aboliſhed, a doctrine any but the <hi>quondam Jack Cade</hi> and his men of rudeneſſe, who would have all Learning and Letters ſuppreſſed, and the Score and the Tally to be the only Books of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, would not only bluſh at, and be aſhamed to own, but ſtand amazed, and diſſolve themſelves into a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that any men ſhould think (as ſome of theſe propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers have done) that the <hi>Lawiers</hi> or profeſſors of <hi>reaſon</hi> ſhould not be fit to intermeddle in the adminiſtration of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> as if reaſon, which God gave for a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and diſtinction to mankind, could be <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> or the mark of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> or that all the praiſes of wiſdom in the Scripture, were only to let men know, that thoſe that had it were not fit to be imployed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:61188:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> That in the right adminiſtration of Juſtice there is a neceſsity of Lawiers, and men of skill and experience.</head>
               <p>FOr the Laws and Cuſtoms of all people, <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and not Chriſtians, Barbarians and not <hi>Barbarians,</hi> do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and practiſe that moſt neceſſary and uſefull <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, Cuilibet in arte ſua credendum, It is beſt to believe every one in his own art, or that wherein he is skilful.</hi> All our Laws and reaſonable Cuſtoms do forbid the uſing of Trades, to which men have not been Apprentiſes for ſeven years <note place="margin">2 &amp; 3 P. &amp; M. 8 Eliz. cap. 11. 1 Iac. cap. 24.</note> together. And ſeveral Acts of <hi>Parliament</hi> would not ſo much as truſt Watermen to row upon the river of <hi>Thames</hi> nor the inhabitants of ſeveral Shires to uſe the art of <hi>Cloathing,</hi> nor ſo much as to make <hi>Caps</hi> or <hi>Pol Davis,</hi> unleſſe they had been Apprentiſes to it.</p>
               <p>The Parliament in the third year of the reign of King <note place="margin">3 H. 8. cap. 11. 1 Ma. cap. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, and ſome other Acts of Parliament made ſince, provides that none but allowed and skill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Phyſicians, and Chirurgions, ſhould practiſe Phyſick, and Chirurgery, for that the practice thereof, by Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers, and unlearned perſons, was to the great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of God, and grievance, hurt, damage, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the People.</p>
               <p>How then can theſe propoſers, or <hi>Trades</hi>-men, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine it to be good for a Common wealth, to baniſh all the knowledge of the <hi>Laws,</hi> and the <hi>means</hi> of doing Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice out of it, and to take in all manner of ignorance in the place of them? or that the Lawiers or men of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſhould be a <hi>burthen</hi> to the Nation; when <hi>Paul</hi> took it to be no diſhonour to have ſate at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:61188:36"/> was more than ordinary carefull of <hi>Zenas</hi> the Lawier, <note place="margin">Epiſt ad Tit. 3. v. 13.</note> and had never gone to <hi>Rome,</hi> not converted ſome in <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro's</hi> own houſhold, if he had not been learned in the Laws, and Privileges of the <hi>Romans,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Iews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the <hi>Dutch</hi> in their united Common-wealth or <hi>Provinces</hi> dare not truſt their ſmalleſt cauſes to their <note n="b" place="margin">Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentar. de Stat. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federat. Provinciar Belgic.</note> 
                  <hi>Commiſſariſsen op de kleyne Saecken,</hi> without a Lawier ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them, and for cauſes of greater conſequence will not in all their Colleges or Courts of Iuſtice want an <hi>Aſſeſſor</hi> or <hi>Syndic,</hi> being a Profeſſor of the <hi>Civil Law,</hi> to direct and guide them.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>Turks</hi> who for the moſt part of them are by the Tyranny and deſigns of their Emperors kept in an ignorance of all Learning and Letters, can have their <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> in their leſſer Courts, and their Iudges in the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vano,</hi> or greater, purpoſely educated, and brought up in that which might enable them unto it, and do not put their <hi>mad</hi> men in places of Iudicature, though they give much reſpect unto them, and take them to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired.</p>
               <p>And when theſe Propoſers can at the ſame time for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing which they have to do in their own affairs, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to find out the moſt able and <hi>skilfull</hi> men, and would think them not to be their Friends at all, or to be ſome of the Inhabitants of <hi>Gonzagua</hi>'s newly diſcovered Country ſlipped down hither through the Moon which ſhould inſtead of a Phyſician bring them when, they are <hi>ſick</hi> a <hi>Carpenter,</hi> or a <hi>Plaiſterer</hi> when they are wounded for a <hi>Surgeon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For can any man think that the Law which was here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore eſteemed to be as hard and difficult a <hi>Science,</hi> as it is noble and worthy, can be practiſed or given out to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:61188:36"/> the people, without any manner of knowledge or learning of it, would theſe <hi>Propoſers</hi> deſire an Act of Parliament, that no ſick and wounded men ſhould any more uſe the help of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> or <hi>Chirurgians,</hi> but ſhould go to the <hi>Justice</hi> of Peace for it? or that no <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter, Maſon,</hi> or <hi>Bricklayer,</hi> ſhould any more med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in the building of Houſes?</p>
               <p>May not the Civil part of the government or power come in a ſhort time to be as much endangered or diſordered, by ſuch an ignorant management of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice as theſe propoſers would have it, as the <hi>Militia</hi> or Military part thereof would be, if all the old <hi>Legions</hi> or Regiments and tryed Souldiers of the <hi>Army,</hi> ſhould by a Law be disbanded and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden the art of war, and young boyes newly come from School, be taken on, and liſted in their places, and none to be Captains or Officers but ſuch as ſhould want their ſight or be blind? Or how little difference will there be betwixtan igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant adminiſtration of <hi>Laws,</hi> and the having of no <hi>Laws</hi> at all.</p>
               <p>Was it <hi>Jethro's</hi> good Counſel to <hi>Moſes</hi> to chooſe able as well as honeſt Judges? and will any <hi>Trades</hi> men, or <hi>Country</hi> men now ſerve the turn? or to what a ſmall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail had it been for the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for <hi>Moſes</hi> to have been learned in the learning of the <hi>Egyptions,</hi> and to have been enabled by God himſelf in his taking the Laws from his own mouth, if ignorant and fooliſh Judges had been appointed under him? or to what end was <hi>Solomons</hi> prayer to God for <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> to go in and out before the people, if thoſe to whom he ſhould commit the care of Juſtice ſhould not know how to execute it? or what would <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle now
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:61188:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſay if he were to plead for his life before ſuch <hi>Iudges</hi> as theſe <hi>Propoſers</hi> would beſtow upon us, or how ſhould he then ſay as he did to <hi>Agrippa,</hi> I think my ſelf hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, <note place="margin">Acts 26. 2 &amp; 3.</note> King <hi>Agrippa, Becauſe I ſhall anſwer for my ſelf this day before thee, eſpecially becauſe I know thee expert in all the Cuſtomes and queſtions which concern the Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe men therfore of Novelty or change may do well to conſider that all things enjoy a happineſs in their reſt, and that a ſetled <hi>conſiſtence</hi> muſt needs be more happy for <hi>States</hi> (ſo called of their <hi>Stabilities</hi>) than to adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the hazard of ſo many changes, as the humours or deſigns of the people ſhall tender unto them, and to believe <hi>Plato,</hi> who was of opinion that <hi>Legum mutatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plato de legibus</note> were <hi>pernicioſae,</hi> that <hi>it was moſt dangerous to change Laws,</hi> and remember what in the Laſt Parliament was delivered by an eminent Member of their own for a moſt certain truth, That the <hi>Law</hi> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr. St.</hi> Iohn <hi>in his argument concerning ſhip mony in Ianuary 1640.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>was the Temple or Sanctuary, whither the People were to run for ſhelter and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge,</hi> and that part of Mr. <hi>Pyms</hi> Speech againſt the Earl of <hi>Sttafford</hi> publiſhed by order of the Houſe of Commons in the late <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſpoken by their own ſenſe and direction, That <hi>the Law is that which puts a difference betwixt good and evil, betwixt just and unjuſt; If the Law be taken away, all things</hi> 
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Pyms <hi>argument againſt the Earl of</hi> Strafford.</note> 
                  <hi>will fall to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, every man will become a Law unto himſelf, which in the depraved condition of Humane nature muſt needs produce many great enormities, Luſt will become a Law, and Envy will become a Law, Covetouſneſſe and Ambition will become Laws, and what dictates and diciſions ſuch Laws will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, may eaſily be diſcerned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Common Souldiers of the <hi>Army</hi> did ſo well <note place="margin">(e) Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and Propoſals of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my p. 11.</note> underſtand it in the year 1647, as they made it their requeſt in their ſecond Apologie to their General the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:61188:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> Lord <hi>Fairfax,</hi> that <hi>(e) Juſtice and Judgement might be dealt to the meaneſt Subject of the Land, according to the old Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the ſaid Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> and the whole <hi>Army,</hi> did <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Excellency Sir</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax <hi>and the Army</hi> 14 Iune 1647</note> afterwards remonſtrate to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that <hi>nothing was more dear and pretious to them in their thoughts, (they having hitherto thought all their preſent injoyments, whether of life, or livelyhood, or nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt relations, a price but ſufficient for ſo rich a bleſsing) that they, and all the Freeborn people of the Nation, might fit down in quiet under their Vines, and under the glorious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Iuſtice and Righteouſneſſe, and in full poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thoſe fundamental rights and liberties, without which they could have little hopes (as to humane conſiderations) to enjoy either any comforts of life, or ſo much as life it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And were at that time ſo far from deſiring the <hi>Lawes</hi> to be taken away, as they deſired of the <hi>Parliament</hi> that <hi>the right of freedom of the People to repreſent to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by way of humble Petition their grievances, (for ſuch things as could not otherwiſe be remedied than by Parliament) might be cleared and vindicated, and that in ſuch things for which men have remedy by law, they might he freely left to the benefit of it,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that in the <hi>Parliament Anno</hi> 1648 (Many of whoſe <hi>Members</hi> were then the Officers of the <hi>Army,</hi> that had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed that Remonſtrante) were ſo well contented with it, as in a Declaration of the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England (g)</hi> expreſſing the grounds of their proceedings, and of ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the preſent Government in the way of a <hi>Free State,</hi> they declared unto the People in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi> that.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They are</hi> 
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Parliament of</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland 17 <hi>March 1648. p. 24. &amp;.</hi> 25</note> 
                  <hi>very ſenſible of the excellency and equality of the Laws of</hi> England, <hi>being duly executed; of their great antiquity even from before the time of the</hi> Norman <hi>ſlavery forced upon us; of the Liberty, and Property, and Peace of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:61188:38"/> the Subject, ſo fully preſerved by them; and (which falls out happily, and as an increaſe of Gods mercy towards us) of the clear conſiſtency of them with the preſent government of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique, upon ſome eaſie alterations of form only, leaving intire the ſubſtance; the name of King being uſed in them for form only, but no power of perſonal adminiſtration of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment allowed to him in the ſmalleſt matter contended for.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They know their own authority to be by the Law, to which the People have aſſented; and beſides their particular inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, (which are not inconſiderable) they more intend the Common intereſt of thoſe whom they ſerve, and clearly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſame, not poſsible to be preſerved without the Laws and government of the Nation; and that if thoſe ſhould be taken away, all induſtry muſt ceaſe, all miſery, blood, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion would follow, and greater calamities if poſsible, than ſell upon us by the late Kings miſgovernment, would certainly involve all perſons, under which they muſt inevitably periſh: and that theſe arguments are ſufficient to perſwade all men to be well contented to ſubmit their lives and fortunes to thoſe juſt &amp; long approved Rules of Law, with which they were already ſo fully acquainted, and not to believe, that the Parliament in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the abrogation of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we have read of a people that died with <hi>quailes</hi> in their mouths, and of a generation of that people did expoſtulate with a <hi>Roman</hi> Magiſtrate for going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to hinder them in their <hi>Self</hi>-deſtruction, we ſhall therefore leave theſe <hi>Propoſers</hi> to the buſie imployment of their own imaginations, and make our addreſſes to the Supreme authority, who being called together for the works of <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and bringing good intentions along with them, have a power to give a ſtop to that <hi>Fury,</hi> is now amongſt a ſmall part of the <hi>People,</hi> but enough to undo all the reſt: Humbly
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:61188:38"/> beſeeching them to <hi>reſcue</hi> out of their hands, the Laws and <hi>Birthright</hi> of the people, and to reach out their hands to preſerve that Law of <hi>Property,</hi> which God himſelf by Thundrings and Lightenings pronounced from Mount <hi>Synai,</hi> and wrote <note n="i" place="margin">8th. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Decalogue</note> a ſecond time with his own <hi>Finger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Judges and profeſſors of the Law, and alſo all Perſons intereſſed or concerned in any loſſe may happen by any alteration thereof, may be heard or adviſed withall in what particulars may be charged a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Laws</hi> in being, or thought fit for reformation, and to take into their conſideration. That in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in the Body <hi>natural,</hi> the <hi>Cure</hi> is never gone about by a total <hi>diſſolution,</hi> nor any part of it intended<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cut off even in caſe of <hi>Gangrene,</hi> where there is any hope to keep life, or to cure without it.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Petitions</hi> which have been againſt the <hi>Laws</hi> are not the voice or general outcry of the <hi>People</hi> in their ſeveral <hi>Counties,</hi> or made by the conſent or approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>major</hi> or any conſiderable part of them, but are an <hi>Engine</hi> or <hi>Artifice</hi> of ſome people never made uſe of till theſe times of <hi>Troubles,</hi> to advance their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and <hi>conveniences,</hi> and bring ruine to others, by petitioning in the names of a whole County or <hi>Province,</hi> of which many times not one in every thouſand of the Inhabitants ever knew or heard any thing before of it. Too many of the <hi>Petitions</hi> concerning publique affairs, having been of late and for ſome years paſt made and <hi>framed</hi> by a <hi>few</hi> in the name of <hi>many,</hi> and many times not in the place or County from whence they ſeem to come, 20000 hands ſaid to be ſubſcribed, when there was not ſo many ſcores, &amp; of thoſe, many ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples names or marks put to it, that were meerly led or
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:61188:39"/> ſeduced unto it, eighty Schools Boys have at once ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed their names to a Petition by the procurement of their <hi>School Maſter,</hi> ſome have had their names ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed when they were never privy unto it, and others that could not write or read, have been drawn to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer their names to go along with a Petition, was for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters than they were informed of.</p>
               <p>And that if all the People of this <hi>Nation</hi> were but freely called together by <hi>Tribes</hi> and <hi>Wards,</hi> or Centuries to give their votes concerning our Laws, as the People of <hi>Rome(k)</hi> were, to peruſe and approve the Laws of the <hi>Ten Tables</hi> brought from <hi>Athens,</hi> and to ſpeak and give their voices as freely as they did then, there would be one thouſand for or to every one that ſhould appear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, would not only conſent to the continuance of the <hi>Laws</hi> and Court of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> we have in being, but be moſt earneſt <hi>Petitioners</hi> for them.</p>
               <p>And would be pleaſed if upon a free &amp; full hearing, as hath been lately granted in the matters of <hi>Tithes,</hi> any thing ſhall be found fit to be abrogated or taken away, they to conſider,</p>
               <p>That in the Acts of Parliament of 27 <hi>Henry 8. cap. 28. &amp; 31 Henry 8. cap.</hi> 13. Touching the diſſolution of <hi>Abbies,</hi> there is a ſaving of all Corodies profits &amp; penſions, due to any other than the Donors, &amp; their Heirs, &amp; <hi>Abbots</hi> &amp; <hi>Abbeſſes,</hi> &amp;c. In the Act for eſtabliſhing <hi>Laws</hi> &amp; Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in <hi>Wales.</hi> 34 &amp; 35 <hi>Hen. 8. cap.</hi> 26. There is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for the Kings Officers for their <hi>Offices</hi> and Fees. In the power given by Parliament to Queen <hi>Mary</hi> in the firſt year of her reign, to diſſolve, alter, unite, or put into one, the Courts of <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> Wards, &amp; <hi>Surveys,</hi> Augmentation, and <hi>Dutchy of Lancaſter;</hi> there is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe <hi>ſaving</hi> of all annuities, penſions, fees, ſtipends, or
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:61188:39"/> ſums of money, which they might or ought lawfully to have, by any letters patents or grant of the ſaid Court of <hi>Augmentation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that if the Queen ſhould annex any of the ſaid Courts to the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> it ſhould be with a ſaving to all perſons of all Offices, of keepers of Chaſes, Parks, Houſes, and the profits thereof, and all Rents, Annui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Fees, &amp;c. with a <hi>proviſoe,</hi> that that Act ſhould not extinguiſh or take away from any perſon any Fees, or Sums of Money which they Lawfully had before the ſeventh of <hi>Iuly</hi> then laſt paſt: That in the diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Abhies</hi> by <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. proviſion was made, and penſions given for life to ſuch as had places or imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in them, as to Readers, <hi>Curats,</hi> &amp;c. and the like: and Corodies or <hi>proviſion</hi> of diet made into a yearly penſion granted out of <hi>Abbies</hi> and Priories ſaved to thoſe that had right to them, many of which are to this day enjoyed by the purchaſers of them.</p>
               <p>That in the Act of <hi>Parliament 3 Jacobi, cap.</hi> 16. For the bringing of the <hi>new river</hi> water to <hi>London,</hi> recompence and amends was to be made and given before hand to ſuch as ſhould be endamaged by it.</p>
               <p>That in the Act of <hi>Parliament 7 Iacobi, cap</hi> 19 for the continuance &amp; repair of a <hi>Weare</hi> upon the River of <hi>Exe,</hi> near the City of <hi>Exceſter,</hi> recompence is provided for any that ſhall be loſers thereby, for that (as the words of the Act are) it ſtandeth with the rule of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> that thoſe which ſhould receive ſo great benefit by it, ſhould yeeld competent and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>recompence</hi> to ſuch as ſhould ſuſtain any loſſe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment thereby.</p>
               <p>That in the putting down of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> in <hi>Scotland</hi> in the late King reign, the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> did think
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:61188:40"/> fit to allow to the <hi>Biſhops</hi> yearly penſions or mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance during their lives, and ſuffered them to enjoy it.</p>
               <p>That in the laſt Parliament of <hi>England</hi> ſatisfaction was promiſed to the Officers and Clerks of the Court of Wards upon the diſſolution thereof, and ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended as the Lord <hi>Say,</hi> and Sr <hi>Penjamin Rudiard</hi> had ſome thouſands of pounds paid or promiſed unto them, and a Committee was appointed to conſider of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of every <hi>Clerks</hi> place, and their loſſes ſuſtained by it. The Wives and Children of Miniſters that were put out of their Benefices, and of <hi>Delinquents,</hi> were allowed a <hi>fifth</hi> part of their Husbands eſtate. And that in the <hi>Propoſals</hi> or Petitions for taking away of <hi>Tithes,</hi> there is a deſire or intention to give to them a maintenance equivalent by ſome other way. That in the Act of the Parliament 29 <hi>May,</hi> 1649. for the draining of the <hi>Lincoln</hi> Shire and <hi>Cambridge</hi> Shire Fenns, the <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> have power to make ſatisfaction to ſuch perſons, whoſe Intereſt or Lands, ſhall be made worſe in quality or condition, by the draining of them, proportionable to their loſſe and damage. That <note place="margin">2 Reg. 23. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioſias</hi> king of <hi>Iuda</hi> in his <hi>reformation,</hi> and turning to the <hi>Lord</hi> with all his <hi>Soul</hi> and with all his <hi>might,</hi> did breaking down the high places permit the Prieſts (though Cauſers of groſſe Idolatry) (and more pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant than any which do now belong to the <hi>Law</hi>) to eat of the unleavened bread among their Brethren. That by the rule of our Saviour Chriſt in the <hi>Goſpel</hi> we are to <hi>do</hi> as we would be <hi>done</hi> unto. And that the promiſe in the firſt Act of this Parliament to be as carefull of the Peoples property and liberty as of their own lives and eſtates, will not be performed without having rightly informed themſelves before hand of what they
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:61188:40"/> would put down or alter, hearing thoſe that are <hi>concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> and giving them a juſt recompence, for what ſhall be thought fitting to be taken away.</p>
               <p>Which if for a general good may (for ſuch part of the Law as ſhall be found fit to be abrogated or taken away) be done.</p>
               <p>With content to all <hi>People,</hi> and according to natural and common equity.</p>
               <p>By a Publique and general <hi>Aſseſsment,</hi> or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way of certain ſatisfaction for it.</p>
               <p>That ſo there may be a mutual <hi>preſervation</hi> of the people, no ſighing of <hi>multitudes</hi> of poor, or broken in <hi>Spirit,</hi> nor <hi>complaining</hi> in our Streets.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:61188:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>By the Authors abſence from the Preſſe the Errata's following have eſcaped the Printer, which the Reader is intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to amend, or ſupply.</head>
            <p>IN Page 9. line 12. adde [<hi>which</hi>] in l. 33. dele [<hi>for</hi>] in p. 16. l. 7. r. [<hi>Jeſuitical</hi>] in l. 33. r. [<hi>and</hi>] p. 17. l. 6. r. [<hi>abſtract</hi>] in p. 19. l. 9. r. [<hi>or</hi>] for [<hi>as</hi>] in l. 10. r. [<hi>the mistake of the Judges</hi>] in p. 20. l. 1. r. [<hi>and</hi>] in p, 20. l. 25. dele [<hi>but</hi>] in l. 32. r. [<hi>now be had for it</hi>] in p. 25. l. 8. r. [<hi>may then</hi>] in p. 26. in l. 3. of the title of Ch. V. r. [<hi>of this</hi>] in p. 26. l. 7. r. [<hi>Syllan</hi>] in l. 15. r. [<hi>Reformation of</hi>] in p. 28. l. 14. r. [<hi>have been</hi>] in p. 29. l. 1. r. [<hi>and from</hi>] in l. 10. r. [<hi>they did not</hi>] p. 31. l. 25. r, [<hi>or fit</hi>] in p. 32. l. 19. r. [<hi>it is</hi>] p. 33. l. 1. r. [<hi>new modeld</hi>] in p. 34. l. 5. dele [<hi>to</hi>] in l. 6. r. [<hi>Aſſiſtant</hi>] in the latter end of l. 32. dele [<hi>the</hi>] in p. 35. l. 4. r. [<hi>rightly</hi>] in l. 10. dele [<hi>and</hi>] and r. [<hi>can no more be kept from</hi>] in l. 11. dele [<hi>can no more be kept from</hi>] and in l. 12. adde [<hi>and</hi>] in l. 12. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le [<hi>ſave</hi>] in l. 17. r. [<hi>ſhould</hi>] in p. 36. dele [<hi>and</hi>] in p. 38. l. 23. adde [<hi>that</hi>] in p. 39. l. 26. r. [<hi>Canon</hi>] in p. 40. l. 23. r. [<hi>will little help the buſines</hi>] l. 25. r. [<hi>and to oppoſe</hi>] l. 29. r. [<hi>be</hi>] in p. 41. l. 3. r. [<hi>or if</hi>] in l. 14. r. [<hi>had adviſed</hi>] in l. 25. r. [<hi>that ſhould</hi>] in p. 47. l. 5. r. [<hi>the</hi>] in p. 49. l. 11. r. [<hi>ſecurity</hi>] in l. 33. r. [<hi>and</hi>] p. 50. l. 23. r. [<hi>were</hi>] in p. 51. l. 3. in the Margent, r. [9 <hi>H. 3. cap.</hi> 11.] in p. 54. l. 6. r. [27 <hi>H. 8. cap.</hi> 5.] in p. 55. l. 21. r. [<hi>Serjeant</hi>] p. 57. l. 14. r. [<hi>attachments upon</hi>] l. 18. r. [<hi>Withernam</hi>] in p. 62. l. 9. r. [<hi>to</hi>] in p. 74. l. 6. r. [<hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin</hi>] in l. 24. r. [<hi>in</hi>] in p. 69. l. 23. dele [<hi>in</hi>] adde [<hi>in Anno</hi>] in p. 46. l. 3. r. [<hi>one hundred and Thirty thouſand</hi>] in p. 24. l. 16. r. [<hi>allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>] in l. 17 dele [<hi>to Bricklayers and Carpenters.</hi>]</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
